<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The celestiall publican A sacred poem: liuely describing the birth, progresse, bloudy passion, and glorious resurrection of our Sauiour. The spirituall sea-fight. The mischieuous deceites of the world, the flesh, the vicious courtier. The Iesuite. The Diuell. Seauen seuerall poems, with sundry epitaphs and anagrams. By Nathanael Richards Gent.</title>
            <author>Richards, Nathanael, ca. 1600-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115928</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851145</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851145</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16405</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10732)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16405)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1079:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The celestiall publican A sacred poem: liuely describing the birth, progresse, bloudy passion, and glorious resurrection of our Sauiour. The spirituall sea-fight. The mischieuous deceites of the world, the flesh, the vicious courtier. The Iesuite. The Diuell. Seauen seuerall poems, with sundry epitaphs and anagrams. By Nathanael Richards Gent.</title>
                  <author>Richards, Nathanael, ca. 1600-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[176] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Roger Michell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-L (-L7,8).</note>
                  <note>A2, containing dedication "To the heavenly lover of divine poems", is often cancelled.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title page has "Richarde".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:2"/>
            <p>THE CELESTIALL PVBLICAN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sacred Poem:</hi> Liuely deſcribing the Birth, Progreſſe, Bloudy Paſſion, and glorious Reſurrection of our SAVIOVR.</p>
            <p>THE SPIRITVALL SEA-FIGHT.</p>
            <p>The Miſchieuous Deceites of <hi>The</hi> WORLD, <hi>The</hi> FLESH, <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icious Courtier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> IESVITE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> DIVELL.</p>
            <p>Seauen ſeuerall Poems, with ſundry Epitaphs and Anagrams.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathanael Richards</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>COELVM CVPIO.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for <hi>Roger Michell.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:3"/>
            <head>THE AVTHOR.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>N o man ſo high, but er'e he die may fall.</l>
               <l>A ll Fleſh is fraile, all ſubiect vnto thrall;</l>
               <l>T her's no content on Earth, none certaine bred</l>
               <l>H ealthfull; to day we liue, to morrow dead.</l>
               <l>A rt, nor Promotion, mends not each mans ſtate,</l>
               <l>N or are the Greateſt Men moſt Fortunate.</l>
               <l>A duancement's but a Smoake, Delight a Toy,</l>
               <l>E ach glit'ring Pompe, each Soule ſeducing Ioy,</l>
               <l>L ike Hell-bred Poyſons worke the Soules annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>R eiect all lewd, vile, vaine affecting pleaſure,</l>
               <l>I ntend thy future good Celeſtiall Treaſure,</l>
               <l>C onteſt with Sinne; Heau'ns holy Armour weare,</l>
               <l>H e that will conquer, he muſt Patience beare,</l>
               <l>A t ſuch rare Combats; Sacred aide is ſent</l>
               <l>R eſpecting Man, all danger to preuent,</l>
               <l>D eare is the Loue of God, in him delight,</l>
               <l>S eeke Heau'nly Ioyes, thoſe comforts infinite.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:3"/>
            <head>TO THE HEAVENLY LOVER OF DIVINE <hi>POEMS.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>GOod Bookes, Good Minds beſt pleaſe, where bad Mindes be,</l>
            <l>Deſert ſhall ſtill be raild at, Vice paſſe free,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Enuie, Debate, Pride, Flatterie, and a</hi> whore;</l>
            <l>The Vicious minded Foole, mindes nothing more.</l>
            <l>Harlots, for hot ſinne-offerings ſhall finde</l>
            <l>Fauour, and Friends, to them the World is kinde,</l>
            <l>But when the wealth of <hi>Soules,</hi> in <hi>Vertues Line</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Leuells Man's crooked <hi>Thoughts,</hi> to thoughts <hi>Diuine.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>'Tis ſleighted then; Moſt <hi>Worldlings,</hi> like falſe Friend,</l>
            <l>Loue not for <hi>Vertue,</hi> but their owne baſe Ends.</l>
            <l>Times Lordly Churle, deepe read, in Errors Schoole,</l>
            <l>Eſteemes Plaine-Dealing, but a <hi>Vertuous</hi> Foole:</l>
            <l>Therefore to thee, whoſe Sacred Soule deſires</l>
            <l>Celeſtiall Solace, <hi>Heauenly</hi> Holy fires.</l>
            <l>To thy Religious thoughts, apt to preuent,</l>
            <l>And fly from Sinne; to thee I this preſent.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Here's no <hi>Luxurious <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> to pleaſe the Eares</l>
               <l>Of Whoriſh Mindes (ſtranger to bleſſed Teares.)</l>
               <l>No Court-Confounding Complement, nor ſtile</l>
               <l>Offeigned Poeſie, nor baſe Flatties Guile:</l>
               <l>Soule-ſuffering Griefe for ſinne, I here expreſſe;</l>
               <l>Wiſhing to All, Immortall happineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>True Penitence gaines Heau'n; throwes Sinners downe</l>
               <l>To raiſe them vp to an <hi>Immortall Crowne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Deuoted to Your Vertues,</hi> NATHANAEL RICHARDS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:4"/>
            <head>THE CELESTIALL PVBLICAN.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I That haue imperfections on my head,</l>
               <l>Paſt Starres in number, or thoſe ſands that ſpread</l>
               <l>The vaſt Seas bottome; ſhall not I confeſſe,</l>
               <l>How oft 'gainſt God, I deſp'rately tranſgreſſe,</l>
               <l>Put off Repentance ſtill from day to day,</l>
               <l>Abuſe his Mighty Patience, ſtill delay</l>
               <l>His dread Command; And like a ſenſeleſſe Sot,</l>
               <l>Vnmindefull of his Mercies, minde them not:</l>
               <l>No ſooner doe I finde a good thought take me,</l>
               <l>But from that Vertue, Fleſh and Blood doe ſhake me,</l>
               <l>The longer life, the more I ſinne, and fall</l>
               <l>From bad to worſe, from worſe to worſt of all.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:5"/>Let others boaſt their goodneſſe, for my part,</l>
               <l>Wretch that I am, I haue a ſinnefull Heart.</l>
               <l>So tyde and bound, fetter'd and chain'd within</l>
               <l>So ſtrong a Priſon; ſuch a Maze of ſinne,</l>
               <l>That 'tis as farre vnlikely for me worme</l>
               <l>E're to winde out, as for to raiſe a Storme,</l>
               <l>Or ſlacke a Tempeſt; Workes of Wonder ſtand,</l>
               <l>Farre from the Reach of Mortals weake command,</l>
               <l>None but the Hand of God, his ſpeciall Grace,</l>
               <l>Can pull me forth the Dungeon of diſgrace.</l>
               <l>'Tis God that frees poore Man from all the Vices</l>
               <l>Of this Worlds wicked villanous Entices.</l>
               <l>And ſhall I then, in impious wayes vneuen</l>
               <l>Offend ſo good a God; Defend me Heauen.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:5"/>My trembling Conſcience tels me, I haue beene</l>
               <l>A very fearefull Sinner, Slaue to ſinne;</l>
               <l>Of all Men, moſt vnworthy of Saluation;</l>
               <l>My ſinnes deſerue Heauens wrath, Hell &amp; damnation,</l>
               <l>Yet Mercy, Mercy Lord, Mercy I craue,</l>
               <l>Shield my ſad ſoule from th' infernall Graue.</l>
               <l>*Strangle my growing ſinnes in their beginning,</l>
               <l>*Demolliſh Lord in me Cuſtome in ſinning.</l>
               <l>*For that is ſuch a kinde of deſp'rate thing</l>
               <l>*Men dreame not on; O 'tis a damned ſting!</l>
               <l>*And thus it creepes on vs; thoughts that are bent</l>
               <l>*To Euill, get Delight, Delight Conſent,</l>
               <l>*Conſent drawes Action, Action Cuſtome breedes,</l>
               <l>*And as the Sick-Man,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> (whom his owne death feedes)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:6"/>*Cuſtome at large, takes ſenſe of ſinne away,</l>
               <l>*Sends ſoules to Hell, when 'tis too late to pray,</l>
               <l>The Doome ſupernall neuer findes returne,</l>
               <l>To call thee backe to Grace; thinke on't, or burne.</l>
               <l>Thinke Heau'ns ſweete, ſiluer, Saints-Bell, toles all in,</l>
               <l>To fright thee eu'ry Morne from vggly ſinne.</l>
               <l>Let Mercy, eu'ry Euening (which do's keepe</l>
               <l>Thee from Day-dangers, Death reſembling ſleepe)</l>
               <l>Be to thy ſoule a Prayer Booke, t' imprint</l>
               <l>Teares in thine Eyes; Griefe in thy Heart of flint.</l>
               <l>Be it ſo, heauenly Father, vnto me,</l>
               <l>To me, and eu'ry one; Make vs to ſee</l>
               <l>And ſhunne Sinnes Cuſtome; with thy ſacred wings</l>
               <l>Guard vs from Danger, Bleſſed King of Kings,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:6"/>Thou that at Home, abroad, at Sea, on land,</l>
               <l>Here, there, and eu'ry where, didſt euer ſtand,</l>
               <l>My ſure Protector, 'gainſt griefes infinite,</l>
               <l>Danger, the Iawes of Famine, Worlds deſpight,</l>
               <l>Sickneſſe, ſad diſcontent, when I and Care,</l>
               <l>Shooke hands with ſorrowes Minion deepe deſpaire,</l>
               <l>At that moſt wretched Time (my thoughts lockt vp</l>
               <l>Beyond all hope of helpe;) then Mercies Cup</l>
               <l>I freely taſted; bleſſed be thy Name</l>
               <l>To me (my Gratious God,) proue ſtill the ſame.</l>
               <l>In my Extreames of griefe, I call'd on thee,</l>
               <l>Mercifull God, and thou didſt ſet me free,</l>
               <l>Thou wert my onely Comfort in diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Food, Rayment, all my Cure in heauineſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:7"/>My true Phyſitian in vnruly madneſſe,</l>
               <l>Celeſtiall Muſicke, in my ſadeſt ſadneſſe,</l>
               <l>Though all the World forſake me, God is kinde,</l>
               <l>He ſolace giues to my diſconſolate minde,</l>
               <l>O be the ſame for euer, may no ill</l>
               <l>Seduce my ſoule to diſobay thy will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While others careleſſe of their Soules true health</l>
               <l>Greedie (like Hell) hunger for worldly wealth,</l>
               <l>Preferment, Pride, th'inſatiate Diuell, Luſt,</l>
               <l>Luxurious Fare, and vainely put their truſt</l>
               <l>In glaſſie Glory, couzening State behauiour,</l>
               <l>In valour Conqueſt, and Monarchall fauour.</l>
               <l>While Soules thus erre, O thou the Lord of light,</l>
               <l>Make me Heauen's Champion, Vertues Fauourite.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:7"/>*Field Honor's but a Vapour, the ſound breſt</l>
               <l>*Puts on Church Armour; Faith, and ſleights the reſt.</l>
               <l>*In loue to Vertue, and true godly feare,</l>
               <l>*Dwells Honour, not in Darts, Bow, Sling or Speare,</l>
               <l>*Not in vaine Beautie, Strength, the Pride of Wit,</l>
               <l>*Preſuming Riches, Learning, Valour, Credit,</l>
               <l>*High Birth, Nobilitie, nor Grauitie,</l>
               <l>*Humanitie, nor yet Virginitie;</l>
               <l>*But in the Humble Soule, whom holy Storie</l>
               <l>*Speakes, to maintaine God, and the Goſpels Glorie,</l>
               <l>*The King, and Kingdomes ſafety, Churches Peace,</l>
               <l>*The Virgins Right, Widdowes, and Fatherleſſe:</l>
               <l>*Theſe are the Noble ſteps which euer waite</l>
               <l>*On Vertues Court, 'tis the true way of State</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:8"/>*That neuer failes (as ſacred Scripture ſaith)</l>
               <l>*The humble, meeke, Religious Knights of Faith.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Heau'nly Father, giue me Grace to fly</l>
               <l>Delight in ſinne, or ſuffer me to dye:</l>
               <l>*Pleaſures are poyſons to this Soule of mine,</l>
               <l>*There's no true Ioy on earth; but what's diuine.</l>
               <l>Lord, teach me for to prize this world at naught,</l>
               <l>Vpon thy Bleſſedneſſe be all my thought.</l>
               <l>*Make me (my God) in hate to impure liues,</l>
               <l>*Kicke at that Life, which Life of Heau'n depriues.</l>
               <l>Make me to feele, thoſe wonted holy fires,</l>
               <l>Which rapt my ſoule in ſanctifide deſires,</l>
               <l>(Rauiſht all ſenſe) and with admir'd amaze,</l>
               <l>Expos'd me, to that bleſſed burning blaze</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:8"/>Of glorious contemplation; thoughts diuine</l>
               <l>Then like Heauens Tapers in my Soule did ſhine;<note place="margin">Simile.</note>
               </l>
               <l>But now that Glory failes; my ſoule hath ſeru'd</l>
               <l>Folly ſo long; 'tis readie to be ſteru'd.</l>
               <l>Darke ſinnes deſire hath dimm'd the Chriſtall ſight,</l>
               <l>Of Meditation, turn'd my Day to Night,</l>
               <l>To diſmall Night; where onely I may ſee</l>
               <l>My ſelfe alone, ſtand like a deſolate Tree</l>
               <l>Forſaken of all her Leaues; the Fruite dead,</l>
               <l>And eu'ry Branch of comfort withered.</l>
               <l>Naked performance, of Heauens ſacred Word,</l>
               <l>Pulls Hell on me; Me thinkes the flaming ſword,</l>
               <l>Of Gods iuſt vengeance, houer's o're my head,</l>
               <l>Th' Element burnes,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> the ſtarres like molten Lead</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:9"/>Threaten deſtruction; while diſtreſſed I,</l>
               <l>Like a condemned wretch ſentenc'd to die,</l>
               <l>Stand quaking at the Horrour, dreadfull woe</l>
               <l>Shiuers my ſinfull ſoule. What ſhall I doe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pitty me King of Thunder, Heau'n, and Earth,</l>
               <l>Mercifull Maker; thou that didſt giue me Birth,</l>
               <l>Thou that canſt muſter Angels in the skie,</l>
               <l>To ſafegard ſoules from blacke impietie,</l>
               <l>Thou that doſt feede, and clothe, and ſtill perſeuer</l>
               <l>To giue me Health, be mercifull for euer.</l>
               <l>I that am poore, weake, feeble, and too apt</l>
               <l>By the worlds whoriſh wayes to be entrapt:</l>
               <l>I that am ſlothfull, dull, and negligent,</l>
               <l>Vnmindfull of thy dread Commandement,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:9"/>Beſeech thy pardon, forgiue my coldneſſe</l>
               <l>In ſeruing thee; pardon that ſinfull boldneſſe.</l>
               <l>Pardon all idle prate; ſinnes rotten talke,</l>
               <l>Let not my ſteppes tread that accurſed walke</l>
               <l>Which leades to lewdneſſe, baſe delight in Pleaſure,</l>
               <l>Deſire of Pompe, Vaine-glory, Tott'ring Treaſure.</l>
               <l>Deale not, O deale not with me as my merit</l>
               <l>Truely deſerues; driue out the vggly ſpirit</l>
               <l>Of all vncleanneſſe from my filthy fleſh,</l>
               <l>(My drooping ſoule with ſanctitie refreſh.)</l>
               <l>Shrowd me beneath thy ſacred Countenance,</l>
               <l>Giue me thy Seruant <hi>Dauids</hi> Repentance,</l>
               <l>The Patiency of <hi>Job, Paul's</hi> Puritie,</l>
               <l>And ſoule-afflicted <hi>Peters</hi> weeping eye:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:10"/>With holy Teares, Lord, make me to reiect</l>
               <l>The ſinne I (ſinne-ſicke ſinner) moſt affect.</l>
               <l>Heare me (Miraculous Maieſtie) and giue</l>
               <l>A Period to my cares, let me not liue</l>
               <l>Fruſtrate of heau'nly thoughts; O ſend redreſſe</l>
               <l>(Thou bidſt me write) keepe me from Idleneſſe,</l>
               <l>From all ill Company, All waies vniuſt,</l>
               <l>Sinne, Satan, and the Laborynth of Luſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>*Like <hi>Joſeph</hi> (Mighty Maker) make me fly</l>
               <l>*The tempting Baites of Beauties burning Eye.</l>
               <l>*Diuert my ſad diſtreſſed ſoule from vice,</l>
               <l>*And Rauiſh me with loue of Paradice.</l>
               <l>*Let not my wand'ring Eyes ſwimme in the fire</l>
               <l>*Of Luſt-ſtung lookes; nor let the looſe deſire</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:10"/>*Of womans naked Paps, burne out mine Eyes</l>
               <l>*With ſenceleſſe gazing; make me to deſpiſe</l>
               <l>*All baſe deſires, ſinnes of ill-gouern'd youth,</l>
               <l>*All wicked Cuſtomes, gainſt thy ſacred Truth.</l>
               <l>Suffer me, Worme vnworthy, not in vaine</l>
               <l>To call on thee, let me ſome comfort gaine</l>
               <l>Or kneele for euer; happie man were I</l>
               <l>To kneele, and pray, and praying thus to die.</l>
               <l>My Armes are ſpread, come ſempeternall Eſſence,</l>
               <l>Rauiſh my ſoule; come bleſſed penitence,</l>
               <l>Giue me a thouſand ſtabs; my ſoule has need</l>
               <l>Of many thouſand Teares; then let it bleed</l>
               <l>Pierce, pierce my ſtubborne Heart; make that the Inne</l>
               <l>Of Grace, which yet is but the houſe of ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:11"/>
               <l>At my dull follies I'le no longer wincke,</l>
               <l>Sorrow ſhall be my Pen, ſad Teares my Incke,</l>
               <l>Miſery my Paper, whereon I'le write</l>
               <l>The ſorrowes of my ſoule, my Youth's delight,</l>
               <l>My Paths of Pleaſure, prodigall expences,</l>
               <l>My ſcarlet Crimes, and all my blacke offences.</l>
               <l>This Booke I'le Dedicate vnto my Heart,</l>
               <l>My Heart, chiefe Actor, in ſinnes Tragicke part,</l>
               <l>My Heart vnprincely, Reuelling within</l>
               <l>My Body, that Banquetting Houſe of ſinne.</l>
               <l>There chain'd to th' Magicke Muſicke of free-will,</l>
               <l>Riots in poyſon'd pleaſures, lewdly ill.</l>
               <l>All that belongs to th' Body eu'ry part,</l>
               <l>(My ſoule alone excepted) ſerues my Heart,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:11"/>Beſt pleas'd, and beſt at eaſe with pleaſures Bane,</l>
               <l>Moſt glad, to be moſt bad, and in that vaine</l>
               <l>Traitor to Truth; Each Limme a Mortall Foe,</l>
               <l>To worke my vniuerſall ouerthrow,</l>
               <l>And to that end, with rude inſatiate eyes,</l>
               <l>Runne all a whoring after vanities,</l>
               <l>Soule-damning Banquets, Pompe, bewitching ioy,</l>
               <l>Forſake eternall Glory for a Toy;</l>
               <l>Debarring hope of Heau'n, and ſweete Saluation,</l>
               <l>For moment pleaſure, licoriſh damnation.</l>
               <l>O falſe, falſe Heart, falſe to thy deareſt friend,</l>
               <l>Wound me no more, for pittie make an End.</l>
               <l>I pittie thy blacke life, nor can forbeare</l>
               <l>For thee, to ſhed, many a bleeding Teare.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:12"/>Thou art my foe, and yet to ſee thee feed</l>
               <l>Fat for Hells ſhambles my poore ſoule do's bleed.</l>
               <l>Bleeds inward, vndiſcern'd of any Eye,</l>
               <l>Except my God, and my owne miſery.</l>
               <l>What ſhall I doe? faine would I ſhunne the ſinne</l>
               <l>My frailty moſt delights to wander in:</l>
               <l>And yet I cannot; when I ſtriue gainſt vice</l>
               <l>To ſtand moſt firme, I'me tript vp in a trice.</l>
               <l>*Oh what a miſery 'tis to haue a minde</l>
               <l>*For to be truly honeſt, well inclinde</l>
               <l>*And not to be ſuffer'd; ſuch is the ſtate,</l>
               <l>*Of my ſad bleeding ſoule vnfortunate.</l>
               <l>Poore ſoule, that liues like Fortunes foot-ball toſt,</l>
               <l>In hazard eu'ry minute to be loſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:12"/>As is the ſhip 'mong Rocks,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> ſteerd by the skill</l>
               <l>Of an imperfect Pilats deſp'rate will.</l>
               <l>Which, like a fruitleſſe naught reſpected fly,<note place="margin">Simile.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Careleſſe of danger, paine or miſery,</l>
               <l>Cutting the Ayre, flies at ſelfe-will ſo faſt,</l>
               <l>Till in the Spiders web 'tis caught at laſt.</l>
               <l>So pleaſure, ſoothing pleaſure, doth beguile,</l>
               <l>The ſinfull Body with her couert guile,</l>
               <l>Being the onely cauſe, when life for breath</l>
               <l>During her ſhort ſpace, vainly ſtriues gainſt death,</l>
               <l>Then like a maſt-leſſe Barke in ſtormy weather,<note place="margin">Simile.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The ſoule driues vp &amp; downe, it knowes not whether,</l>
               <l>At laſt, for life miſſe-led, (ſinnes that excell)</l>
               <l>Body and ſoule at once, Iumpe into Hell.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:13"/>*O thou the King, of thoſe eternall fires</l>
               <l>*Which ſpangle Heauen; good God grant my deſires</l>
               <l>*Infuſe in me thy Grace, or I ſhall ſtray</l>
               <l>*And ſo become a fearefull Caſt-away.</l>
               <l>*Helpe, or I ſinke, belowe the lowe degree,</l>
               <l>*Of ſinnes extreameſt infelicitie.</l>
               <l>*Come, come Lord Ieſus, O come thou and giue</l>
               <l>*Helpe to my helpleſſe ſoule; I that doe liue</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>Like the diſtreſſed Bird, trapt in a Snare,</l>
               <l>Caught by a lime-twig flying from the Ayre;</l>
               <l>In which diſtreſſe, for comforts ſweete reliefe,</l>
               <l>Poore Innocent, with wings adds woe, to griefe,</l>
               <l>So fares my ſoule, ſtriuing ſinnes ſnare to fly</l>
               <l>Forc'd by deceit, liues ſnar'd in penury.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:13"/>Accompaned with comfortleſſe deſpaire,</l>
               <l>With ſobs, and grones, and ſelfe-conſuming care</l>
               <l>In Sable ſorrow ſits, there ſighs, and mournes,<note place="margin">Simile.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Waſtes, and conſumes, like a ſpent Taper burnes</l>
               <l>Onely for a ſlaſh, ready to goe out,</l>
               <l>With multitude of ſinnes circl'd about.</l>
               <l>The very thought do's ſhake me, and the feare</l>
               <l>Rowze my flint Heart,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> that like a frighted Deere</l>
               <l>Amazed ſtands; attaints mine eyes of treaſon,</l>
               <l>Thoſe eyes exclaime, againſt the eyes of reaſon,</l>
               <l>The eye of reaſon, blames their wanton ſight</l>
               <l>As ouer rul'd by fooliſh appetite,</l>
               <l>Each guilty of their fault, to ſinne ſtand thrall,</l>
               <l>No Limme but helps, th' oppreſſed ſoule to fall,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:14"/>*Man at the beſt, his vertu's very little,</l>
               <l>*His ſtate a Bubble, at the ſtrong'ſt moſt brittle,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>*Mans life is like a Game at Tables, where</l>
               <l>*A good chance happ'ning; if you doe not there</l>
               <l>*Mend it with ſome good play; the ſad Games loſſe</l>
               <l>*Will vexe thy grieued ſoule, proue the ſole croſſe</l>
               <l>*To all thy comforts; All quietneſſe than</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>*Leaues thee; and like a drunken ſeruing-man,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>*Which at his maſters moſt need goes aſtray,</l>
               <l>*Is euer ſure, ſtill to be out o'th way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What ſhall I doe? Where, whether ſhall I fly?</l>
               <l>Here, there, I know not where, lie downe and dye,</l>
               <l>Vp ſoule to Heau'n, there get a glorious Crowne,</l>
               <l>I am too weake, too vile, ſinne puls me downe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:14"/>O my vnworthineſſe, my ſhame, my ſinne</l>
               <l>When ſhall I ſhake thee of, when, when beginne,</l>
               <l>No; wilt not bee, can I not doe the good</l>
               <l>I would? Muſt I be rul'd by fleſh, and blood?</l>
               <l>Weepe on, weepe on, diſſolue hard heart of flint,</l>
               <l>Melt, melt thou ſtony rocke, Teares neuer ſtint</l>
               <l>Drop Marble Mount, drop to a crimſon flood,</l>
               <l>Sinke my ſinnes in Seas of penitent blood.</l>
               <l>Come folded Armes, and you ſad Eyes, ſad Heart,</l>
               <l>Come Soule oppreſt with ſorrow, play thy Part,</l>
               <l>Haſte to ſome gloomy-groue, there all alone</l>
               <l>On the greene mantled Earth, ſigh, ſob, and grone,</l>
               <l>Spend pretious time, with ſacred thoghts that beares</l>
               <l>Heau'n in their Eyes, true Vertue in their teares,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:15"/>Complaine I will to fortune, not that whore</l>
               <l>Which makes leane art, &amp; pale-fac'd wiſdome poore,</l>
               <l>Ile not complaine to her; but to that Ens</l>
               <l>Almighty Fortune; in diuineſt ſenſe,</l>
               <l>Groueling on Earth for ſinne; Ile caſt forth groanes,</l>
               <l>Sighes ſhall conuert to Teares; Teares into moanes.</l>
               <l>Then will I ſtart, from ground my Body raiſe</l>
               <l>Shoote mine Eyes vpward; againſt Heau'n I'le gaze</l>
               <l>Thinke on my God; my God, whoſe ſacred Will</l>
               <l>I haue abuſ'd; my God moſt iuſt to kill</l>
               <l>Damne Soule, and Body, my rememb'rance blot</l>
               <l>Out of the Booke of Life, I that forgot</l>
               <l>(In midſt of all vaine ioyes, Intemp'rate healths</l>
               <l>Looſe wanton chambering laſciuious ſtealths.)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:15"/>All-ſeeing Heauen; a God ſo good, ſo great,</l>
               <l>He that to feed vs with Spirituall meate,</l>
               <l>Tooke humane ſhape; came downe from Heau'n,<note place="margin">The Natiuitie of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </note> to Earth</l>
               <l>Enter'd the World; at whoſe ſoule-ſauing Birth</l>
               <l>The euerlaſting gates of Mercy ſtood</l>
               <l>Open to all; His houre of fleſh and blood,</l>
               <l>Turn'd night to day, Heau'ns glittering Angell came</l>
               <l>And to poore men, poore ſheepheards did proclaime</l>
               <l>A Sauiour borne, ſinnes fury to controule,</l>
               <l>Neuer was ſuch ſweet muſicke to the ſoule,</l>
               <l>Before his comming; the Natiuitie</l>
               <l>Of Chriſt brings mortals firme felicitie.</l>
               <l>*Milde was his Birth; his Life creations wonder,</l>
               <l>*His death, deaths terror; O thou God of thunder,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:16"/>*Maſter of mans ſaluation, all the Earth</l>
               <l>*Reapt plenitude of Ioy, when thou tookſt Birth,</l>
               <l>*Mortalls were bigge with ſinne, villany ripe,</l>
               <l>*Hells dreadfull Dragon, ready for to gripe</l>
               <l>*Soules in his vggly pawes; But then ſtept in</l>
               <l>*Our Sauiour; he redeemd loſt ſoules, whoſe ſinne</l>
               <l>*Gaue them to death eternall; bleſſed houre,</l>
               <l>*Bleſſed Natiuitie, thrice bleſſed powre,</l>
               <l>*Me thinkes at thought of thy Natiuitie,</l>
               <l>*I lie perfum'd in Immortalitie.</l>
               <l>When Chriſt was borne, all were new borne agen,</l>
               <l>Nere came like Muſicke to the hearts of Men:</l>
               <l>Angels for ioy, clap their Celeſtiall Wings,</l>
               <l>And eu'ry Saint, eu'ry Crownd Martyr Sings</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:16"/>
                  <hi>(Magnifico Deum)</hi> to mortalls peace</l>
               <l>The calme of Conſcience, and ſhall mortals ceaſe</l>
               <l>Their glad expreſſions? No, let hate to vice</l>
               <l>Diſſolue ſinnes cloud; Eccho to Paradice</l>
               <l>Our Sauiours welcome, let vs neuer more</l>
               <l>Lie downe to our diſhonours like a whore<note place="margin">Simile.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Dead to good councell; neuer let darke deedes</l>
               <l>Defile the Soule; Lets roote vp all the ſeedes</l>
               <l>Of Pride, Luſt, Enuie, Hatred, and in place</l>
               <l>Plant wiſedome, meeke humility and grace.</l>
               <l>*Chriſts Glory came cloathd in humility,</l>
               <l>*To teach our Hell-bred Pride, Ciuility.</l>
               <l>*Borne of a Virgin, came to the world a ſtranger</l>
               <l>*His Palace an Oxe-ſtall, his Bed a Manger:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:17"/>O're whoſe obſcure aboad, Heau'ns Taper ſhinde;</l>
               <l>And to the ſoules of wiſeſt Men diuinde</l>
               <l>Great Natures wonder; pointed them the way</l>
               <l>To finde the worlds Redeemer; they obay</l>
               <l>Made towards that fixed ſtarre which in the skie</l>
               <l>Was the bleſt Virgin Maries Canopie.</l>
               <l>To Beth-lehem they came; there with hearts glad</l>
               <l>Ador'd the King of Glory, poorely clad.</l>
               <l>Nor could blood thirſtie Herods ſtrict command,</l>
               <l>Nor bloody butchering of Babes withſtand</l>
               <l>His bleſſed Birth; whoſe admiration brings</l>
               <l>Ioy to the world; bleſt be that King of Kings,</l>
               <l>He that to cure ſinnes Leaporous diſeaſe</l>
               <l>A Heauenly Progreſſe fetcht, the Geſte theſe:</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:17"/>C<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>HR<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>IST'S Setting forth from's Celeſtiall PALACE,<note place="margin">The Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant of Glory.</note> Lodg'd in the <hi>Virgins</hi> Wombe; from that bleſt PLACE, To th' <hi>Manger</hi> went; from <hi>Manger</hi> to the <hi>Croſſe;</hi> From <hi>Croſſe</hi> departed (with his deare Blouds loſſe) Vnto the SEPVLCHER; there made all euen, And ſo Return'd, Gloriouſly Home to HEAVEN. To HEAV'N, from whence LORD let thy SACRED FIRE, GLISTER vpon my SOVLE, whoſe ſole Deſire, Begges MERCY for my Sinnes, makes knowne to THEE, THOV that haſt RAVIHST ALL, haſt Rauiſht Me.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:18"/>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The Paſſion of <hi>Christ.</hi>
                  </note>Thirty three yeeres Chriſts ſanctity did were</l>
               <l>The Cloth of our Redemption, and did beare</l>
               <l>Times heauy yoake of croſſes, that we might,</l>
               <l>With eaſe ſuſtaine all wrongs; in him delight</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>*Like Martyr'd <hi>Stephen,</hi> whoſe lowd crying grones</l>
               <l>*Gain'd Heau'n ith' middle of a ſtorme of ſtones.</l>
               <l>*Loue lead him on; in Death this Saint was Taſter,</l>
               <l>*And firſt, that follow'd his Immortall Maſter</l>
               <l>*Chriſt Crucifide; whom none that truly heares,</l>
               <l>*But ſure 'twill thawe their frozen hearts to teares.</l>
               <l>*Chriſts whole Life was a Martyrdome, and Croſſe,</l>
               <l>*Actiue, and Paſſiue, and his deare bloods loſſe</l>
               <l>*The Tragicke Part, the bloody Sceane which none</l>
               <l>*But he himſelfe muſt Act, and Act alone.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:18"/>*Alone for vs, (Heau'ns Glorious Lampe of Grace</l>
               <l>*Grou'ling on Earth) fell on his ſacred Face,</l>
               <l>*He that is euer Lord of Mercies ſeate,</l>
               <l>*Water'd the Garden Cedron with the ſweate</l>
               <l>*Of bloody Browes, and Body; heauineſſe,</l>
               <l>*And deadly ſorrow, ſeiz'd his bleſſedneſſe:</l>
               <l>*A kiſſe betray'd him, and a periur'd lie,</l>
               <l>*Was the Reward for all his puritie,</l>
               <l>In ſcorne, this Prince of Heau'n was buffetted,</l>
               <l>Spighted, ſpitted at, Extreamly ſcourged,</l>
               <l>Yet Torture ne'r mou'd him; he was ſilent,</l>
               <l>In all his bitter ſuffrings patient.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Neuer did Earthly King, (free from annoy)</l>
               <l>Receiue his Crowne, nor with a greater ioy</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:19"/>Went to his Coronation Dignifide</l>
               <l>As Glories King; went to be Crucifide.</l>
               <l>In him the Iewes derided Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>Condemned Innocence, ſcourg'd Pietie,</l>
               <l>*Head, Hands, Side, Feet, they to the Croſſe did Fixe</l>
               <l>*Made him all o're a bloody Crucifixe.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>*Satan and Death like ſawcie ſerieants went</l>
               <l>*To ſeize on him; to ſheere that Innocent</l>
               <l>*Bleſt Lambe of God; But he who was to ſaue</l>
               <l>*All that belieu'd; they had no power to ſhaue,</l>
               <l>*His Patience, Death, and Diuels force did quell</l>
               <l>*He tooke the Great <hi>Leuiathan</hi> of Hell</l>
               <l>*With the hooke of his Croſſe; made him his ſlaue</l>
               <l>*Captiu'd the Diuell, and ſubdued the Graue,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>*Like a long lookt for Booke, Chriſt in the Preſſe</l>
               <l>Was kept, to come in Print forth, for to bleſſe</l>
               <l>*Our ſoules with that Saluation which do's giue</l>
               <l>*New Life, whereby Eternally wee liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:19"/>
               <head>INRI.</head>
               <l>Suffer'dſt the Crowne of Thornes t'empale thy Braine,<note place="margin">The Key of Heauen.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Which downe thy Checkes forc'd ſhowres of Bloud to raine:</l>
               <l>Suffer'dſt the piercing LAVNCE, that like a FLOVD</l>
               <l>Sluc'd, from thy wounded Side, thy pretious BLOVD</l>
               <l>Nayl'd to the Croſſe; there CHRIST loſt Soules to winne,</l>
               <l>Suffer'd, the World's huge pond'rous weight of Sinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Deare Sauiour ſweet, ſweet was thy deare Compaſſion,</l>
               <l>Dearely expreſt in that moſt bitter PASSION;</l>
               <l>When whipt and ſcourg'd, thou mildly ſuffer'dſt all,</l>
               <l>Blowes, Buffets, Blaſphemies, VIN'GER and GALL,</l>
               <l>Inſulting Foes Reproach, Mockes, Scoffings, Scorne,</l>
               <l>Thy SINEWES to be Rackt, thy BODY Torne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heau'ns Wrath, Hel's Rage;</l>
               <l>On CHRIST, all Torments fell</l>
               <l>To ſaue our Soules fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe blew flames in Hell.</l>
               <l>At which th' amazed EARTH with horrour ſhooke,</l>
               <l>Darkeneſſe poſſeſt the WORLD, Day Light forſooke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:20"/>
               <head>INRI.</head>
               <l>CAN muddie Mortals minde their Actuall EVILLS,</l>
               <l>And not <hi>Chriſts</hi> SVFF'RINGS? (Such reſemble Deuils:)</l>
               <l>HAPPY the MAN, whoſe ſacred SOVLE is bent,</l>
               <l>FOR <hi>Christ's</hi> ENDVRINGS, firmely to REPENT,</l>
               <l>What <hi>Tongue?</hi> What <hi>Pen?</hi> Not all Man's <hi>Wit</hi> can tell</l>
               <l>CHRIST'S Torments; they exceeded paines in Hell:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her wonted courſe; the Sunne obſcur'd his Light,</l>
               <l>At Death of IESVS CHRIST; that bloudy ſight</l>
               <l>Made HELL to quake; Diuels with Admiration,</l>
               <l>Tremble to ſee the Cauſe of MANS Saluation!</l>
               <l>Oh the rich thought, ſtrike, ſtrike amazing Thunder,</l>
               <l>Shake Natures Frame; this impious Age with wonder!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And all for MAN,</l>
               <l>Ingratefull, wretched MAN,</l>
               <l>Are we not bound, to loue and feare Him than?</l>
               <l>O, yes, to ſpend whole houres, dayes, months, &amp; yeares</l>
               <l>In true Repentant Showres, and Flouds of Teares.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:20"/>B<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſt, Bleſt, O Bleſt, Be that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity,<note place="margin">The PYRAMID OF <hi>Paradice.</hi>
               </note> Three Sacred Perſons GOD in Vnitie, WHOSE glorious Rauiſhing Reſurrection, Reſtor'd Vs (loſt) to Grace, Oh PERFECTION! Purifie thou my Soule, my Heart, my Minde: Snatch mee from Earth, to Heau'n make mee inclin'd, Wholy to Thee, (All worldly Pompe deſpiſing) Fixe my THOVGHTS euer, On thy Bleſſed RISING: Giue MEE A Sempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, To Thy ALL-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious high Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence. I that am clog'd with ſin, &amp; wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, Deſp'rate thoughts hunting after Worldlineſſe;) Thy Bleſt Protection craue, cleare the great ſcore, Of all my fowle miſdeeds, that I no more So great a Sinner prooue; Lord let my ſtrife, Againſt my ſinnes, Raiſe me from Death to Life. And from the Foote of vggly ſinnes diſgrace, Mount, mount, my SOVLE, to th' Pyramid of Grace.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:21"/>
               <l>Did each one truely know the true delight,</l>
               <l>Wherein the wiſe contemplate Heau'ns rich ſight,</l>
               <l>'Twould fright th'exceſſiue ſinners God-leſſe face,</l>
               <l>Make him, as in a Glaſſe ſee his diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Teare op'e his eyes, that all amaz'd with horrour,</l>
               <l>Trembling he may behold with dreadfull terrour,</l>
               <l>A guard of Furies, ſucking at his ſoule,</l>
               <l>That he may ſee his ſinnes, horrid and foule,</l>
               <l>(Liue as in ſulphurous flames;) diſcerne his Euill,</l>
               <l>See the fierce Deuill, and ceaſe to be a Deuill.</l>
               <l>Ceaſe from damnations Heire, licentious life,</l>
               <l>Ceaſe from extreames in ſinne, ſoule-murdring ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Abhorre to ſtudie ſtate with greater Zeale</l>
               <l>Then Zeale to Heau'n, or the ſoules Common-weale</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:21"/>Abhorre with ſolemne Oathes periur'd to teare,</l>
               <l>And racke the Name of Chriſt dreadleſſe of feare</l>
               <l>Wounding afreſh (with trembling feare I write)</l>
               <l>Wonder of Angels, that great God of Light.</l>
               <l>His wounds, with Othes of wounds, fleſh, bloud &amp; hart,</l>
               <l>(Horrour of darkeneſſe) O blaſpheming part!</l>
               <l>Too too much vs'd 'mong God-leſſe ſoules, who ſtill</l>
               <l>Infinite good pay with infinite ill.</l>
               <l>As if no thought remain'd of future good,</l>
               <l>No teares for him, that ſhed his pretious bloud,</l>
               <l>But as the comely Actor,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> whoſe faire part</l>
               <l>Vpon the ſtage preſents an honeſt heart</l>
               <l>For two houres ſpace, a Vertuous Noble Minde,</l>
               <l>His Sceane expir'd, baſely to vice inclinde,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:22"/>Drinke, Drabs, and Oathes, making no other vſe</l>
               <l>With his faire Part but with exceſſe abuſe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>*O you that ſtand on Pynacles of ſtate</l>
               <l>*Let not the World deceiue you, leaſt too late</l>
               <l>*From off your ſlipp'ry height you come in thrall,</l>
               <l>*o paſh your ſelues in peeces paſt recall.</l>
               <l>*Sell not fare Lord-ſhips, to keepe Lady-ſhips,</l>
               <l>*Nor ſucke damnation from a ſtrumpets lips.</l>
               <l>*Touch not thoſe Spells of <hi>Sparta,</hi> let e'm Rot</l>
               <l>*When Vertue rules in Man, Luſt liues forgot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One onely Iemme, that's all the ſtore I haue,</l>
               <l>Great of that little nothing, which ſhall craue</l>
               <l>Of Heauens Greate En's, not for my ſelfe alone,</l>
               <l>But for thee Reader, thee, and euery one,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:22"/>Rareneſſe of Rare example, and withall</l>
               <l>An euerlaſting skie of Grace to fall</l>
               <l>Vpon our warre on Earth, deſiring Heauen,</l>
               <l>For wayes on Earth are crooked, all vneuen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>*Saue me, O ſaue me, thou Eternall Terror</l>
               <l>*To damned ſoules, I doe confeſſe each Error,</l>
               <l>*The many thouſand ſinnes, vnſeene, vnfelt</l>
               <l>Which long, too long in my hard heart haue dwelt,</l>
               <l>*To thee, to thee, thou Euer-liuing being</l>
               <l>*Of an Eternall Maieſtie All-ſeeing,</l>
               <l>*With penitent Heart I come, I call, I cry,</l>
               <l>*Pardon my ſinnes, helpe thou All-viewing Eye.</l>
               <l>*Looke downe Soule-ſauing ſacred God of Truth</l>
               <l>*Forgiue, th' infinite follies of my youth.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:23"/>*Shield me Diuinitie from Satans Ginnes</l>
               <l>*Lord lay not to my Charge my Parents ſinnes:</l>
               <l>*Glory of Goodneſſe in thy Mercy heare mee;</l>
               <l>*Let Hate, Reuenge, nor Enuie ne'r come neare mee,</l>
               <l>*Let neither Pride, nor hope of gaine deceiue mee,</l>
               <l>*Nor pleaſure, nor the want of Meanes bereaue mee</l>
               <l>*Of ſenſe; leaſt ſenſeleſſe wholy I deſpaire,</l>
               <l>*And ſo become the wretched Childe of care.</l>
               <l>*O ſacred Sauiour make me euer trie</l>
               <l>*To liue by honeſt Meanes, or let me die;</l>
               <l>*Though griefe, and I, haue well acquainted beene,</l>
               <l>*Lord let me neuer grieue, but for my ſinne.</l>
               <l>*So ſhall thy Mercy, ne'r forgetfull ſtand</l>
               <l>*While I haue Tongue, a Pen, a Head, a Hand.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:23"/>
            <head>THE SPIRITVALL SEA-FIGHT.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>EM'prour of Angells, O thou King of Starres,</l>
               <l>Mans perfect ſolace 'gainſt ſins bloody Wars</l>
               <l>When I behold, with contemplation Eye</l>
               <l>The ſiluer Spangles of thy Glorious skie;</l>
               <l>Me thinkes in that Blew-paper-Booke of Heau'n,</l>
               <l>I ſee waies of Mortalls all vneu'n</l>
               <l>The wretched ſoule of Man in euery Place</l>
               <l>Liues as in Hell on Earth, without thy Grace,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:24"/>Temptation on Temptation, paſt controule</l>
               <l>Alures the Body, to betray the Soule.</l>
               <l>Hell's Blacke Prince, Troopes of ſpirits eu'ry day</l>
               <l>Inuade my ſinne-ſeidg'd-ſoule; Furies diſplay</l>
               <l>Infernall Banners; while the Drumme of Death</l>
               <l>Beates a dead March; and e're I can take Breath</l>
               <l>Sounds ſhrill Alarums; hot Aſſaults beginne</l>
               <l>The ſoules fierce Fight; muffl'd in cloudy ſinne,</l>
               <l>I liue beſet, Millions of ſpirits round</l>
               <l>Shoote at my ſoule; I ſtand on no firme ground</l>
               <l>But tread on earth, as on a Ball of Ice</l>
               <l>I cannot ſtand, nor ſtirre for ſlip'ry Vice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Soul's a Ship, toſt on the Mountaine Seas</l>
               <l>Of this vaſt World, ſhe neuer liues ar eaſe;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:24"/>*Her ſayles are ſighes, her Anchor deepe deſpaire,</l>
               <l>*Her Compaſſe Error, her ſad Pilot, Care;</l>
               <l>Farre of from ſafeties ſhore, floates on the waues</l>
               <l>Of fearefull billowes, Soule deuouring Graues.</l>
               <l>Rough, bluſt'ring, ſtubborne ſtormes, yeeld no reliefe</l>
               <l>On euery Shrowd, Each Tackling, hangs a griefe:</l>
               <l>Death like a darke cloud, beſets euery Place,</l>
               <l>Here Rocks of Ruine, their Pyrates lie in Chaſe</l>
               <l>In euery corner, Miſchiefes hourely lurke,</l>
               <l>*Pride fights againſt vs like a furious <hi>Turke;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>
               </l>
               <l>*Luſt like a trech'rous <hi>Spaniard;</hi> murd'ring <hi>French,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>*Like an infected poyſon's loathſome ſtench,</l>
               <l>*Gluttonie like a <hi>Germaine,</hi> drunkenneſſe</l>
               <l>*Like a <hi>Dutch Dun-kercker;</hi> whoſe impiouſneſſe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:25"/>*Stiles him the Maſter Gunner, to giue fire</l>
               <l>*To all ſinnes blacke Artillery, Hells Ire</l>
               <l>*Infernall chaine-ſhot, All ſoule-murd'ring ſtrife,</l>
               <l>To ſinke Man's weather-beaten ſhip of Life,</l>
               <l>Which to gaine Grace, no ſooner weighs Anchor,</l>
               <l>Sets ſayle for ſafety, but ſtraight ſinnes Canker,</l>
               <l>The deuouring Diuell, Pyrate for Hell,</l>
               <l>Chaſing flyes after, and with blacke Arts ſpell</l>
               <l>Commands to ſtay; ſometimes with beauteous formes</l>
               <l>With ſongs of Syrens ſometimes; ſometimes ſtormes.</l>
               <l>Such pitchie Tempeſts, to be night the way,</l>
               <l>As if the horror of the lattet day</l>
               <l>Frighted the World; ſo ſtops the ſoule from bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Shoots through, and through her, ſo ſhe ſteers amiſſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:25"/>Then as in bloudy Sea-fights Men may ſee<note place="margin">Simile.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Times ſacrifice to valour, no man free</l>
               <l>From deſp'rate danger; euery one maintaines</l>
               <l>The terrour of the Fight (though with their braines</l>
               <l>Daſht in each others Faces.) Vitall breath,</l>
               <l>Loſt in a fighting flame; blood, and death:</l>
               <l>Bullets, and Batteries, couers the ſhip all o're</l>
               <l>Her diſmall deckes with horror, purple gore,</l>
               <l>And ſcatterd limmes; ſo the ſoules Pinnace</l>
               <l>In her ſpirituall fight ſinnes do's deface,</l>
               <l>Murders our beſt of thoughts, like raging Seas,</l>
               <l>Winds, ſtormes &amp; tempeſt driue vs where they pleaſe.</l>
               <l>The poore afflicted ſoule, Satan ſo blinds,</l>
               <l>It knowes not where ſhee is; by whyzing winds.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:26"/>Now toſt toth' top of all the Azure Skie,</l>
               <l>Now tumbling as to Hell, with frighted Eye,</l>
               <l>Her Flag of ſinnes defiance Tempeſt-rent.</l>
               <l>Her Sayles torne all to Rags, her Maine-maſt ſpent;</l>
               <l>All out of Order: toſſing to, and fro,</l>
               <l>The ſoule diſtreſt, knowes not which way to goe.</l>
               <l>With gentle calme, check Satan's black ſtorme, Lord,</l>
               <l>Wee ſhipwracke elſe, Diuels will come a Board</l>
               <l>Burne with Hells wildfire, Flame, Ruine, Race,</l>
               <l>Blot our ſoules hope, helpe Miniſter of Grace.</l>
               <l>Safeties in Heau'n, in this vncertaine Life</l>
               <l>Nothing but Hell-bred quick ſands, Warre, and ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Soule-killing vapours, worldly vanities,</l>
               <l>Thicke clouds of vice Perpetuall miſeries,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:26"/>
               <l>There is a Voyage, to the Holy Land</l>
               <l>In which the Truth, our bleſſed <hi>Card</hi> muſt ſtand</l>
               <l>The Holy Ghoſt our <hi>Pilot</hi> to direct</l>
               <l>The ſteerage of our courſe from ſinnes neglect,</l>
               <l>Toth' Hauen, of Heau'n; that happy <hi>Port</hi> of Reſt,</l>
               <l>Saluations Guard, true <hi>Cape</hi> of Comfort bleſt.</l>
               <l>There, Heauens bright Maieſtie, our Sauiour ſweet,</l>
               <l>Sits with the Hand of Mercy, for to Greet</l>
               <l>And waft vs to him; O may all that ſtray!</l>
               <l>Sayling along the Coaſt of ſorrow, Pray,</l>
               <l>Pray vnto him, hee'l guide their wandring Barke,</l>
               <l>Tempeſt toſt hourely in the dreadfull Darke.</l>
               <l>If thou be Sea-ſicke call vpon him, and he</l>
               <l>Shall ſoone with Health's ſweet ſolace comfort thee;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:27"/>Rebuke the raging windes, Times blackeſt ſtorme,</l>
               <l>And to a calme, Skie-ſwelling Seas reforme:</l>
               <l>No Rocks, Gulfs, Sands, nor Seas cloud-kiſſing waues</l>
               <l>Sinnes dreadfull Sea-fright, nor the deſp'rate braues</l>
               <l>Of Pyrates, none ſhall hurt; let then thy care</l>
               <l>See thy weake veſſell Rigg'd, well Man'd with prayer</l>
               <l>And then launch forth, hoiſt ſayles, and when you ſpie</l>
               <l>The <hi>Cape</hi> of good hope, keepe it in thine eye.</l>
               <l>Let holy thoughts, death threatning ſtorms o'recome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>That whatſoeuer chance there ſhall become,</l>
               <l>The veſſell of thy Body being foule,</l>
               <l>Make ſure to ſaue the paſſenger, thy ſoule.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>*He valiant, onely Vertuous is that can</l>
               <l>*Subdue his Sinnes; Hees the true Noble Man,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:27"/>*Ther's perfect valour, he true glory winnes,</l>
               <l>*He's the true Souldier, that ſubdues his ſinnes:</l>
               <l>*Breakes through the pikes of ſinne, all fiends that are</l>
               <l>*In Hell, or Diuels ruling in the Aire,</l>
               <l>(*Forcing his way to Heau'n deſpight all charmes)</l>
               <l>*Enchantme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, dead-ſleeps, all ſoule-flayling harmes)</l>
               <l>*Wreſtling like <hi>Jacab,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note> conſtant in his fight</l>
               <l>*Mindfull of his maieſtick-Makers ſight.</l>
               <l>To ſuch belongs the Euerlaſting Crowne</l>
               <l>Of ſempeternall Glory, true Ronowne;</l>
               <l>Which to prepare thee for; ceaſe to neglect</l>
               <l>Th' Allmighties ſacred ſeruice, let reſpect</l>
               <l>Feare and true Reuerence to his pretious Word,</l>
               <l>Be to thy ſoule that Helmet, Shield and Sword</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:28"/>Too ſtrong for Sathan, all the fiery Darts</l>
               <l>Of Fiends and furies, Arme thy noble Parts</l>
               <l>Thy Soule, thy Heart, thy Minde, ſtriue to fulfill</l>
               <l>(The Maieſtie of Heauen) his Diuine Will.</l>
               <l>And like the cunning curious Architect</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>Earneſt ſome goodly Building to Erect:</l>
               <l>(Breaking his ſleepe) wholly imployes his minde</l>
               <l>On the drawne Modell; which when he do's finde</l>
               <l>Exact, his Eye dwels euer then vpon it,</l>
               <l>And his affection neuer driuen from it.</l>
               <l>So when to thought we call our Sauiours blood,</l>
               <l>(That ſempeternall platforme of all good)</l>
               <l>Shed for our ſinnes, Let it for euer dwell</l>
               <l>In the Idaea of our Mindes, ſo Hell,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:28"/>Sinne, death, nor deadly deſp'rate diſcontent,</l>
               <l>Can barre the Heau'nly heart from true content.</l>
               <l>*What vggly wormes are wee that dare preſume</l>
               <l>*To pawne our ſoules for pleaſure, dare conſume</l>
               <l>*Our Time on toyes, when as we firmely know</l>
               <l>*Time ſhall decay; we cannot feed, nor goe,</l>
               <l>*Nor promiſe life a Minuite; we paſſe to bed</l>
               <l>*But Ignorant to riſe aliue, or dead.</l>
               <l>*Admit day-light approaches, and the morne</l>
               <l>*Inuites thee forth? thou neuer maiſt returne:</l>
               <l>*Death by a thouſand accidents do's meete</l>
               <l>*Health, Wealth, and Beauty; ſtabs them in the ſtreet,</l>
               <l>*He that leaſt thinkes of death, ſome falling Tyle</l>
               <l>*Timber, or Stone, do's ſuddenly beguile</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:29"/>Him of his life, yea oft' when he refraines</l>
               <l>And ſeekes to ſhun it, daſheth out his braines.</l>
               <l>Theſe Tragicke Truths (true cauſes of diſlike,)</l>
               <l>Me-thinkes ſhould moue vs to repent, and ſtrike</l>
               <l>A terror to our ſoules; force vs to ſee</l>
               <l>Man's outward danger; inward miſery</l>
               <l>Which like an vnreſiſted roaring Tide</l>
               <l>Runnes through our veins, and apts the blood to pride</l>
               <l>To all the ſinnes that are, or euer were,</l>
               <l>O horrid ill! haue wee not cauſe to feare,</l>
               <l>To quake and tremble, when our dull dead Eyes</l>
               <l>(Drunke with the poyſon'd dreggs of ſinne) ne'r ſpies</l>
               <l>The miſchieuous perills, and the blacke affright</l>
               <l>That hourely waite, on the Spirituall fight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:29"/>
               <l>Fiends liue at Sea, and Furies on the Land,</l>
               <l>*Gluttonie for a <hi>Corporall</hi> do's Stand,</l>
               <l>*Au'rice a <hi>Pioner,</hi> Sloth you may ſpie</l>
               <l>*An idle <hi>Gentleman</hi> of a Company.</l>
               <l>*Wrath's the <hi>Serieant,</hi> Enuie the <hi>Colours</hi> gaine,</l>
               <l>*Luſt the <hi>Lieftennant</hi> is; Pride the <hi>Captaine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe in the Heart of euery one take Place</l>
               <l>Where cowardly ſoul's ſhun the bleſt meanes of grace,</l>
               <l>Let vs for euer then reſiſt all Euill</l>
               <l>Wiſedome commands vs to defie the Diuell;</l>
               <l>To combate with our ſinnes; oppoſe temptation,</l>
               <l>Fight againſt Hell the Diuell, and Damnation.</l>
               <l>This for a Caueat take, ſtriue to doe well:</l>
               <l>(Ingratitude to Heau'n, picks open hell.)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:30"/>While Grace is offer'd then, Watch, Faſt, and Pray:</l>
               <l>Ther's no preuention in the latter day.</l>
               <l>*None liues ſecure, that to his Vice liues friend,</l>
               <l>*A Vitious life, oft makes a vitious end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>*Strengthen me, my Creator, make me fight</l>
               <l>*Thy HOLY BATTLE, let not the Worlds delight</l>
               <l>*Diſſwade my ſoule; ſweet Ieſus, for thy merits</l>
               <l>*Enable mee, Rowze my deiected Spirits,</l>
               <l>*Vncharme Hells charme, O Sacred God vntie</l>
               <l>*My fetter'd Soule, let mee not euer lie</l>
               <l>*Lull'd in the Strumpet lap of deadly ſinne,</l>
               <l>*This Minute Sacred Sauiour now beginne</l>
               <l>*To giue Releaſe, and as thou didſt prouide</l>
               <l>*An Army of Angels, for <hi>Eliahs</hi> guide,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:30"/>*Who (to ſecure him guirt with Enemies)</l>
               <l>*Mounted his ſoule from worldly vanities.</l>
               <l>*So Heauenly Day-Star, bleſſed Ieſus end</l>
               <l>*This my Deſigne thy holy Angell ſend</l>
               <l>*To be my Guide, my Guard, my Sacred ſpell</l>
               <l>*Gainſt all Enchantments, witchcrafts, death, &amp; hell</l>
               <l>*So ſhall my Anthem euery morning be</l>
               <l>*Glory of Heauen, ſhew mercy vnto me,</l>
               <l>*To me Times wretch, moſt wretched; vilely baſe</l>
               <l>*Wanting thy ſacred aide, ſpirituall grace.</l>
               <l>*Remember not my frailties; make me to grow</l>
               <l>*Great in thy loue, thou that doſt truly know,</l>
               <l>*Of all the Bleſſings vnto Mortals giuen</l>
               <l>*My chiefe deſire on Earth, is Grace from Heau'n,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:31"/>*The Bleſſing of th' Almighty Lord of Hoaſt,</l>
               <l>*The Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt,</l>
               <l>*Preſerue, be with me, now, and for euer when</l>
               <l>*My Soule is moſt diſtreſt, Amen, Amen.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spes mea Chriſto.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:31"/>
            <head>THE WORLD.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VAine is this <hi>World,</hi> this Strumpet World that can</l>
               <l>Yeeld nothing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant, Loue 'twixt man &amp; man,</l>
               <l>Which next his Maker, ſhould be moſt reſpected,</l>
               <l>Is ſooneſt broake; and moſt of all neglected,</l>
               <l>Ingratefull, vile, the World's a very Whore,</l>
               <l>Proud, rich in Vice, in Vertue moſt, moſt poore,</l>
               <l>Miſſe-led by eu'ry vaine Phantaſticke Toy,</l>
               <l>To forget God, bewitch't with carnall ioy;</l>
               <l>Bundles of Baubles, imbecilitie,</l>
               <l>Biles of Apparell; Botch Nobilitie:</l>
               <l>Lordſhips, Ladyſhips, Foolries and Faſhions,</l>
               <l>Luſt-panting Humours; ten thouſand Paſſions.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:32"/>Rich Men, the more to blame, as this Age goes,</l>
               <l>Debarre houſe-keeping to maintaine gay Cloathes;</l>
               <l>A Rich Caroach, three hunder'd pounds a Gowne,</l>
               <l>Thirty pounds a Smocke, or their Wiues will frowne,</l>
               <l>There is no liuing with them, they muſt ride</l>
               <l>Where, when, and how they liſt in glit'ring Pride,</l>
               <l>High flaſhing burning Brauerie, blinde Eyes,</l>
               <l>Flint Hearts, dull Eares, deafe to all poore Mens cries</l>
               <l>Such is the dullneſſe of Mortalitie,</l>
               <l>And ſuch the World's cold Hoſpitalitie,</l>
               <l>*Each duſtie Magiſt'rate with Brib'rie fed,</l>
               <l>*One robs the liuing, another robs the dead,</l>
               <l>*A third the Arch-Theefe playes by cunning ſtealth,</l>
               <l>*Knaue Knights by Patent rob the Common-wealth,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:32"/>*Ioyne with much, too much, ill iniuſtice, he</l>
               <l>*Zodomiticall Lecher for a greedie Fee</l>
               <l>*Dares licenſe luſt, glad if he may preuaile,</l>
               <l>*(Sucke wealth from proſtitute Harlots;) neuer faile</l>
               <l>Man's minde which moſt his Maker ſhould affect</l>
               <l>(With feare, and trembling, and that true reſpect,</l>
               <l>Belongs to his high Maieſtie) the Net</l>
               <l>Of ſinne ſo ſnares, we worthleſſe wormes forget</l>
               <l>God's Thunder-darting Vengeance, glorious ſtate</l>
               <l>Still forget God, forget to contemplate</l>
               <l>With Rauiſhing Loue, true loue, pure heart, pure eies,</l>
               <l>That's the defect makes hourely miſchiefes riſe,</l>
               <l>*Ambitious Lords Attir'd in Anicke ſhape,</l>
               <l>*Ioy in the wayes of Luſt, Murder, and Rape,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:33"/>*Ladies with charmes, tricks, humours, that they haue,</l>
               <l>*Abuſe their Lords, diſpatch them to the Graue.</l>
               <l>*The Iealious Husband (miſchieuous in ill)</l>
               <l>*Through vaine ſuſpect, his conſtant wife to kill.</l>
               <l>*The careleſſe Cleargy man in his degree</l>
               <l>*Satan corrupts; makes for a golded fee</l>
               <l>The greedy Lawyer fed by Clients ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Brib'd angels take, for the true Angell life.</l>
               <l>Iuſt Iudge, the vniuſt duſtie Magiſtrate,</l>
               <l>Father the Sonne, the Sonne the Father hate,</l>
               <l>Brother, the Brother, proſecute to death,</l>
               <l>Quarrell for Toyes; ſtop one anothers breath.</l>
               <l>The world do's hourly tempt fooles worldly wiſe,</l>
               <l>The deceitfull Tradeſman, that ſeemes preciſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:33"/>And is an arrant knaue; to thinke the honie</l>
               <l>And onely bleſſed life, ſtill to get mony.</l>
               <l>Mockes at the poore mans vertue, and in pride</l>
               <l>Stiles him a vertuous foole; thus knaues deride</l>
               <l>The pouertie of Men, which do's as farre</l>
               <l>(In Heauenly wealth) tranſcend them, as a ſtarre</l>
               <l>The richeſt Iemme on Earth; But tis not ſo</l>
               <l>With the worlds wealthy worldling; they ſay no,</l>
               <l>Rich enough, Honeſt enough; all they can</l>
               <l>Aimes at the outward, not the inward man.</l>
               <l>*Pouertie made a ſcoffe, a ſcorne, a winde:</l>
               <l>*Gold ſmothers Vertue, blackeſt Actions blinde.</l>
               <l>*Gold got in God's name, with an honeſt face,</l>
               <l>*Comes ſlow; but in the Diuels name apace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:34"/>
               <l>Such is the world's condition, Good Men's thrall,</l>
               <l>On Earth ther's no true comfort, none at all.</l>
               <l>*The honeſt minded Scholler, ſhall ne'r lacke,</l>
               <l>*Sorrow nor want of meanes to breake his backe.</l>
               <l>*The pittifull Souldier, in his greateſt need</l>
               <l>*Ha's his throate cut, he ſhall be ſure to bleed,</l>
               <l>*The faire Gameſter, for his milde ſquare play.</l>
               <l>*Is ſooneſt coozen'd, ſure to loſe eu'ry day.</l>
               <l>*The faithfull Louer, ſtill is paid with hate</l>
               <l>*The more in loue, the more vnfortunate.</l>
               <l>Be rich or poore, in high or low Eſtate</l>
               <l>I'th mod'rate Meane, or fully fortunate,</l>
               <l>Inſatiate Mankinde, euer diſcontent,</l>
               <l>Deſires to liue, but neuer liues content.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:34"/>In ſcarcity of Corne, for plentie crie,</l>
               <l>In plenty, ſtraight forget God inſtantly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such is Man's Erring ſoule, which ought to know</l>
               <l>*Lifes, but a long ſad Pilgrimage of woe,<note place="margin">Simile.</note>
               </l>
               <l>*An Arke of trauell, ſhop of vanity,</l>
               <l>*Storehouſe of trifles, Inhumanitie:</l>
               <l>*A Field of Stones; a Path of thornie Prickes,</l>
               <l>*Meadow of Scorpions, Groue of Baſiliſckes.</l>
               <l>The Worlds vnquiet reſt, is all Man's foe,</l>
               <l>*Dangers attend vs, where ſo ere wee goe.</l>
               <l>*Miſchieuous Deceits, Brawles, Quarrels, Fightings,</l>
               <l>*Falſe-hearted Neighbour-hood, baſe back-bitings.</l>
               <l>*Friendſhip's ſo faithleſſe Ripe, full blowne with euill</l>
               <l>*A friend to day, the next for gaine proues Deuill,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:35"/>The World's condition right; 'tis ſlaue to ſinne,</l>
               <l>Beware of it; the worlds a cunning ginne</l>
               <l>*Twill entrap ſoules; call then to God for Grace,</l>
               <l>*Let griefe for worldly Croſſes, ne'r take place,</l>
               <l>*Neuer let ſorrow runne into extreames</l>
               <l>*Vnleſſe for ſinne; ſo ſhall Celeſtiall Beames</l>
               <l>*Glorifie thy Soule, make it Immortall,</l>
               <l>*Free it from ills; what euer can befall</l>
               <l>In this falſe promiſing World; this Maze of woe,</l>
               <l>Where wretched Worldlings know not where to goe</l>
               <l>To winde them out; ſuch are the various wayes</l>
               <l>Of life oppreſſing Yeeres, Months, Weeks and Daies.</l>
               <l>As Proſe ill read, abide too much miſuſing,</l>
               <l>Or Vertuous verſe, when rogues haue the peruſing,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:35"/>*So fares it with the faire, and flouriſhing Line,</l>
               <l>*Of that ſweet Heauenly ſtraine, Poeſie Diuine,</l>
               <l>*Baſely neglected by the Monſter Crew,</l>
               <l>*Of Puff-Paſte muddie Mindes; that piſh, and mew,</l>
               <l>*Make a wry, Cloſe-ſtoole-face; a ſquint ey'd glance</l>
               <l>*At Vertuous verſe; (whoſe ſad miſchance,</l>
               <l>*Is to goe vnregarded,) when the crime</l>
               <l>*Of a laſciuious, Baſtard, Ballet rime,</l>
               <l>(*If baudy enough) though ne'r ſo vnfit</l>
               <l>*Winnes fauour, profit, and the praiſe of wit.</l>
               <l>*Read with delight, and much, too much requir'd,</l>
               <l>*Coppies ſought after, greedily deſir'd:</l>
               <l>*When perfect Poetrie, Muſicke to the ſoule</l>
               <l>Truth's firme Oppoſer 'gainſt crimes filthy ſoule</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:36"/>*(If Read) moſt read for faſhion, ſmall delight,</l>
               <l>*No comfort, no reſpect, but ſcornefull flight.</l>
               <l>*And ſuch is Vertues Foe; the Worlds proud Minion,</l>
               <l>*In whom ther's no true Loue, no perfect Vnion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Diuine Poeſie I lament thy ſtate,</l>
               <l>To ſee thy Beautie diſproportionate,</l>
               <l>So poorely in eſteeme, their's few I ſee</l>
               <l>Or none at all take true delight in thee.</l>
               <l>*This wanton World farre ſooner will approue</l>
               <l>*Ioy in Pot-Poets, louſie Rimeing loue,</l>
               <l>*Or wanton <hi>Ouids</hi> ſtraine, to itch the eare,</l>
               <l>*And ſtirre the blood to luſt, rather then heare</l>
               <l>*The Glorious Godly Aime of Noble Verſe,</l>
               <l>*Which points at Heau'n; and tels vs of that fierce</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:36"/>All-threatning Thunderer; he that deſcries</l>
               <l>Our ſecret deeds; thoſe blackeſt Actions ſpies</l>
               <l>At which, amaz'd. my Muſe ſtands wrapt in wonder,</l>
               <l>Beggs Mercy, Mercy, O thou God of Thunder,</l>
               <l>Or we ſhall ſhipwracke all; All too too blame</l>
               <l>Farre too vnmindfull of God's Sacred Name,</l>
               <l>His Bleſſings day, by day, his, great Mercy</l>
               <l>Long ſuffering, and Excelling Safety.</l>
               <l>Why ſhould we worm's ſtand pretious in Heau'ns ſight</l>
               <l>And not be damn'd to Euerlaſting Night,</l>
               <l>For our Foule erring ſinnes, ſinnes that Excell</l>
               <l>The leaſt whereof, merits the Paines of Hell.</l>
               <l>Hell that this inſtant Gapes, to ſeize this world,</l>
               <l>Deſeruing euery moment to be hurl'd</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:37"/>To endleſſe Flames; but for the Excellence</l>
               <l>Of OVR FATHER'S, wonderfull patience.</l>
               <l>O for the Pen of pure perfection,</l>
               <l>To character Man's imperfection,</l>
               <l>Open the blinde, exceſſiue ſinner's eyes,</l>
               <l>(Force Teares for ſinne) make him, himſelfe deſpiſe</l>
               <l>'Twere Muſicke to the Soule; Diuine delight</l>
               <l>Th'vndoubted Path to pleaſures infinite.</l>
               <l>Holla Commanding Empreſſe of my Braine,</l>
               <l>Whether thus flings my Muſe; diuert thy Straine:</l>
               <l>Man is ſo farre from making God amends,</l>
               <l>That all his waies to wicked Actions bends,</l>
               <l>The World's a Racke, Times Tenter-hooke to ketch</l>
               <l>At mindes moſt honeſt; makes a man a wretch:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:37"/>Thouſands in want, finding no way to cure it</l>
               <l>Hazard the Gallowes, rather then endure it,</l>
               <l>Miſ'ry of Miſeries, when Coyne growes ſcant</l>
               <l>Man's Fortun's Foot-ball, ther's no woe to want;</l>
               <l>It dulls braue witts, when nothing elſe can doe it;</l>
               <l>Tames, and makes deſp'rate when Time brings vs to it</l>
               <l>Want makes a man turne Slaue, vnto a Slaue</l>
               <l>Scoft, ſcorn'd, and flouted at by eu'ry knaue,</l>
               <l>By eu'ry ſilken ſodden-headed Foole,</l>
               <l>That neuer felt Heau'ns ſcourge, nor Miſ'ries Schoole</l>
               <l>Want, broacheth Miſchiefes neuer thought vpon,</l>
               <l>Makes many an honeſt woman wanton.</l>
               <l>Want (like a Madman) makes Men ſweare and Dice<note place="margin">Simile.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Forget their God, turne Vertue into vice.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:38"/>Husband, and wife, the Siſter, and the Brother,</l>
               <l>Compel'd through want, deuoure one another.</l>
               <l>Merchants, Lawyers, yea ſome Diuines will fall</l>
               <l>When want do's ſoundly Gripe, tw'ill trie them all.</l>
               <l>And therefore (As an Antidote) be ſure</l>
               <l>Firſt that thou pray to God, that's the maine Cure</l>
               <l>Gainſt Woluiſh-want; and then bethinke thee ſure</l>
               <l>Vpon ſome honeſt meanes; 'twill new Create</l>
               <l>Thy vnderſtanding, put thee on a way</l>
               <l>With Reu'rent Soule, on bended knees, each day</l>
               <l>To ſerue thy God aright; ſo he from falling</l>
               <l>Proues thy Protector, giues thee a Vertuous Calling</l>
               <l>Heau'n grant the Honeſt Minde may neuer know</l>
               <l>The fierce Aſſaults of want, that Hell of woe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:38"/>Torture of Minde, <hi>Murderer</hi> of <hi>Modeſtie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>High-way to Theft, Cut-throate of <hi>Chaſtitie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Key of <hi>Whoredome,</hi> Bane of that true Loue</l>
               <l>Which many boaſt, but few did euer proue.</l>
               <l>Many vow Loue, for euer to be true</l>
               <l>Yet, when want comes, <hi>Whores</hi> are not more vntrue.</l>
               <l>How ſweetly did that <hi>Sacred Pſalmist</hi> ſing</l>
               <l>And runne <hi>Times</hi> true Diuiſion on the ſtring</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Miſery,</hi> when he of God did craue,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Want,</hi> nor too much <hi>Wealth,</hi> leaſt in the Graue</l>
               <l>Of damn'd <hi>Deſpaire,</hi> much want might haile him in</l>
               <l>And Riches Mount him to the higheſt ſinne:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lackey</hi> his way to lewdneſſe, to miſtruſt</l>
               <l>God's Mercies, and to practiſe wayes vniuſt</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:39"/>A Holy feare ſeiz'd on that bleſſed King</l>
               <l>To dread want's Dangerous Dart, Proud Riches ſting.</l>
               <l>May the Good Man, ſtill thirſt for Mercies Cup;</l>
               <l>Climbe <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſacred Ladder and mount vp</l>
               <l>Into a fiery Chariot, Burning Zeale,</l>
               <l>Liue a bright Angell in Heau'ns Common weale.</l>
               <l>Free from this World; whoſe Pompe, and Brauery,</l>
               <l>Is but a Land of Durt, meere ſlauery,</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:39"/>
            <head>THE FLESH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SInne Acts foule Luſt vpon the Soule while it</l>
               <l>Stands Puritan Punck-like, willing to commit.</l>
               <l>The Fleſh vnto the Soul's a bitter Pill,</l>
               <l>(Sweet guilded Poyſon, Candide o're to kill.)</l>
               <l>Hurrid, Carocht in Pride, which glit'ring ſhowe</l>
               <l>Of ſwelling Pompe, whoſe ſweet Effect is woe.</l>
               <l>Fleſhly delights beget much Miſery</l>
               <l>Makes Couples marrie vnaduiſedly,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:40"/>Thinking Loue tittle tattles, can feed their wiſhes,</l>
               <l>Loue ſoone growes cold, where there is empty diſhes.</l>
               <l>Of all the ſinnes that are, when nothing can</l>
               <l>Ruine the Soule; the Fleſh preuailes with Man,</l>
               <l>His Eyes no ſooner on Deuotion waite,</l>
               <l>But in ſteps Carnall Concupiſcence ſtraight</l>
               <l>She's at his Elbow ſtill, to itch him on,</l>
               <l>Th'vnhappy path to his Confuſion.</l>
               <l>*Chaſte wiues are Saints, women that wantonize</l>
               <l>*Witches, all poyſon, Hell is in their Eyes,</l>
               <l>In which, as in a Wilderneſſe of woe,</l>
               <l>In ſtriuing to get out, on mad men goe</l>
               <l>Starke mad, paſt ſenſe, ſpight of all Books and Schools</l>
               <l>Ruine their Fortunes, proue the Slaues to Fooles</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:40"/>For an alluring Minutes trifling Ioy</l>
               <l>A lewd Inſatiate Longing, a meere Toy.</l>
               <l>*O woman, woman, thy bewitching motion,</l>
               <l>*Fooles wiſedome, mads reaſon, and blinds al deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Fleſh (falſe Traitor like) ſtriues to betray</l>
               <l>The Soule to Hell, for an Infernall Prey.</l>
               <l>Fleſhly delight in Man, feares want of Breath</l>
               <l>More then his God; ſinne, or Eternall Death,</l>
               <l>*When iuſt plagues come, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin-ſick ſots can tremble</l>
               <l>*Make knowne to all the World, how they diſſemble,</l>
               <l>*Pray with the lip, (not heart,) wreſt ſacred Text</l>
               <l>*To ſerue their owne Ends firſt, and then God next.</l>
               <l>*Prouide to liue, in peſtilent Times beginne,</l>
               <l>*Take greater Care to flie from death, then ſinne.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:41"/>*Ther's nothing in our Fleſh, but wickedneſſe</l>
               <l>*Deſire to liue, and obſcene wantonneſſe.</l>
               <l>We forget now that dreadfull diſmall chance</l>
               <l>The Terrible Arrow of Gods vengeance,</l>
               <l>When Death buried farre more, then th' Earth could ſwallow,</l>
               <l>And no man to the Graue his Friend durſt follow,</l>
               <l>O why ſhould Mortals wiſh, long life to liue,</l>
               <l>What Comfort? what true Ioy do's this life giue?</l>
               <l>*Ther's nothing, not one thought that do's vs good,</l>
               <l>*But it is ſtrangled ſtraight, by Fleſh and blood,</l>
               <l>*Holy Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> finding the Fleſh Rebell,</l>
               <l>*deſir'd to be diſſolu'd, proud Fleſh to quell,</l>
               <l>*And Sacred <hi>Symeon</hi> ſung 'gainſt ſinnes encreaſe</l>
               <l>*Lord let thy ſeruant now, depart in peace,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:41"/>Shall ſuch ſoule-ſweetning preparations be</l>
               <l>Forgotten quite; O blinde ſecuritie,</l>
               <l>*Life louing Fortunes, how yea puffe Men vp,</l>
               <l>*To hugge their Follies, drinke damnation's Cup.</l>
               <l>What is it we behold, in this vaine life,</l>
               <l>But dayly griefes and dangers; ſinne, and ſtrife.</l>
               <l>*When my ſoule-erring Eyes, ſtaring behold</l>
               <l>*A dang'rous Strumpet, flame in glit'ring gold,</l>
               <l>*(And murd'ring Beauty; ſparkling from her Eye</l>
               <l>*Burning Temptation) then me thinkes I ſpie</l>
               <l>*My moſt apparent miſchiefe, plainely ſee</l>
               <l>*How I ne'r ſtriue to pleaſe my God, as ſhee</l>
               <l>*Striues to pleaſe Men; ſuch is the flaring Pride</l>
               <l>*Of the vaine Fleſh, it hurts on euery ſide.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:42"/>There's nothing conſtant in vs, if to day</l>
               <l>Vertue we loue, to morrow Vice obay.</l>
               <l>Man at the beſt, is now become ſo fraile</l>
               <l>As what cannot a ſpruce Queane, with a ſmooth Taile</l>
               <l>Make him beleeue; ſuch witchcraft euer fly,</l>
               <l>Luſt reuells, in the Magicke of her eye.</l>
               <l>That ſtar-ſhooting, twinckling eye, do's ne'r ſhine,</l>
               <l>But to the Ruine, of all thoughts diuine.</l>
               <l>Twixt her aluring Lips, there liues a Spell</l>
               <l>To ſucke, and ſincke, and kiſſe a man to Hell.</l>
               <l>Touch but her Palmes, there ſinnes moiſt hand inuite</l>
               <l>To a ſoule-damning Banquet; ſuch delights,</l>
               <l>As often makes the wiſeſt Man an Aſſe,</l>
               <l>Coward, and Foole, Times vitious Looking-Glaſſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:42"/>Licoriſh entice pants on her Naked Breſt,</l>
               <l>Snaring the tim'rous ſoule, to all vnreſt.</l>
               <l>And like a feauers Puſe, t' encreaſe deſire,</l>
               <l>Beates thicke vpon the Heart, ſets all on fire.</l>
               <l>What a notorious Coxcombe vnto ſinne,</l>
               <l>Luſt makes of Man, ſlaue to a whores ſoft skinne?</l>
               <l>What's a delicious Harlot but a Cheater,</l>
               <l>A poyſon'd <hi>Marmalad Boxe,</hi> which rots the Eater,</l>
               <l>A Harlot in her beſt of Brau'rie can</l>
               <l>Be but a kinde of greaſie dripping-Pan,</l>
               <l>So often put to th' fire, it proues a flame,</l>
               <l>So burnes the Baſting-Sticke, ſo Luſt growes tame.</l>
               <l>Loue is a chaſte Queene, noble Wiſedomes Bride,</l>
               <l>Luſt a Hot Whore; for eu'ry Knaue to ride;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:43"/>*Loue is a Virgin ſprung from Vertues Race,</l>
               <l>*Luſt an alluring Strumpet paſt all Grace:</l>
               <l>*Loue is a vertuous wife, Times conſtant Woman</l>
               <l>*Luſt a proud Harlot, the true Scourge of Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The chiefe praiſe of a good wife do's not lie</l>
               <l>In outward ſhew, but inward Pietie,</l>
               <l>If Vertue Rules her blood, ſhe merits Loue,</l>
               <l>If not, I will aſſure thee ſhe will proue</l>
               <l>Like a deceitfull Glaſſe, where Man may ſee</l>
               <l>Hee's meerely Cheated in her; O Miſerie</l>
               <l>*Man makes a woman proud with looking at,</l>
               <l>*A wonderous wanton toy, beleeue that,</l>
               <l>*Marke but the cunning Beautie ſeeing men gaze,</l>
               <l>*And yet not ſeemes to ſee, note but her waies</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:43"/>See how ſhee tempts, with what a charming ſmile,</l>
               <l>Puts poiſon in her Eyes, eyes to beguile,</l>
               <l>Seducing eyes, aim'd at Eternall Light,</l>
               <l>From Heau'n, to looke on Hell, prurient delight,</l>
               <l>Deckt, trimm'd, adorn'd, trickt vp to pull men on</l>
               <l>With Pride of Eyes, to their confuſion.</l>
               <l>Note the varietie of all her charmes,</l>
               <l>The Lazie, idle, ſtretching of the Armes;</l>
               <l>The Yawne, and then the Hey-ho, rolling eie,</l>
               <l>Sicke ſtomacke for the Act; O Luxurie:</l>
               <l>Thy flames, in wanton women, ſtrangely moue,</l>
               <l>*She that delights in Luſt, can neuer Loue.</l>
               <l>Obſerue each geſture, how ſhe takes a pride</l>
               <l>To itch the Bumbe; to friske from ſide to ſide,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:44"/>Mop, mew, bite Lip, and wriggle with the Taile,</l>
               <l>There's not a ioynt about her that ſhall faile</l>
               <l>To catch at Man; be Icie cold as ſtone,</l>
               <l>Shee'l finde a Tricke to melt affection.</l>
               <l>In each behauiour liues a Venome ſnare,</l>
               <l>There's language in the curling of her haire,</l>
               <l>Eyes, Cheeks, Lips, Hands, no motiue Limme ſo weake</l>
               <l>But ſerues to tempt; her very foot ſhall ſpeake.</l>
               <l>Shee'l part each other in ſuch dalling ſort</l>
               <l>As if ſhee'd doe with th' Ayre for want of ſport.</l>
               <l>Croſſe legges, and then with itching thighes &amp; knees</l>
               <l>Open and ſhut the paſſage by degrees.</l>
               <l>Takes pleaſure to be ſeene to wantonize,</l>
               <l>And is beſt pleaſed, to pleaſe Letchers Eyes.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:44"/>*Like thoſe Nice Dames that will in outward ſhow</l>
               <l>*Not wrong their husbands, no forſooth, O no,</l>
               <l>*Not for a World; ſtand on their honeſtie,</l>
               <l>*Quote Scripture, ſymper, looke moſt modeſtly,</l>
               <l>*Sweare and forſweare, ſhould the firſt husband die,</l>
               <l>*Ne're to wed more; Yet marrie preſently,</l>
               <l>*And then proteſt the ſingle life temptation,</l>
               <l>*Phy out vpon 't, foe to Procreation,</l>
               <l>Thus ſeeme in publique pure; but in priuate</l>
               <l>More ſecretly open, more inſatiate</l>
               <l>Then the hot Monkie 'th veneriall Marke</l>
               <l>Skip, friske, and fling, doe wonders in the darke.</l>
               <l>And like the <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> thinke Luſt done by ſtealth</l>
               <l>Dainty, ſecure, ſuddaine, and done for health</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:45"/>*The onely Cure, Luſts raging flames to quench,</l>
               <l>*Is <hi>Aqua lachrimarum;</hi> that will ſtench</l>
               <l>*The wounds, proud Harlots ſo delight to make</l>
               <l>*On the poore ſoule of Man; make him to quake,</l>
               <l>*A fear'd to ſtand on that falſe Rocke of Ice</l>
               <l>*Idleneſſe, feeder of foule Carnall vice,</l>
               <l>*Blacke errors cloud, South fog, which rots the minde</l>
               <l>*Leapours the Soules, and is the Northern winde</l>
               <l>*The cauſe of all ſins Stormes, that dang'rous Flood</l>
               <l>*Luſts ſurging Ocean ſwelling in Mans blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Diuell deſire of Luſt, mee, mee, forſake;</l>
               <l>I charge thee hence, by him that made Hell quake</l>
               <l>By that Almighty One, in ſacred Trine</l>
               <l>All Holy Spels, and Charmes, Magicke Diuine.</l>
               <l>By that ſweet excellent Sacred Puritie</l>
               <l>(Siſter of Angells) Virgin chaſtitie.</l>
               <l>Fly from me all baſe thoughts; be iuſt mine Eyes;</l>
               <l>And be your ſelues, hate wantons witcheries.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:45"/>
            <head>THE VICIOVS COVRTIER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>GOe, harmeleſſe <hi>Satyr,</hi> if thou ſmell a <hi>Rat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Dogge</hi> of Enuie, of the blacke ey'd <hi>Bat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For op'ning the faire Truth, miſconſter ſence,</l>
               <l>Knit the baſe Brow, of daring impudence,</l>
               <l>And wiſely like a <hi>Wolfe</hi>-like Aduocate,</l>
               <l>Make thee dangerous, vile, a thing of hate,</l>
               <l>If honeſt <hi>Satyr</hi> ſuch thou meete, defie,</l>
               <l>Spare not to giue the Fooles and Knaues the lie.</l>
               <l>There was a Time, when hadſt thou play'd the knaue,</l>
               <l>Thou might'ſt haue flouriſht and haue flouriſht braue.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:46"/>Fortune that <hi>whore,</hi> the Worlds aluring Ginne</l>
               <l>She had beene true, hadſt thou beene true to Sinne:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God</hi> knowes I enuie no Man for his Greatneſſe,</l>
               <l>For his Proſperity, true Worthineſſe,</l>
               <l>I ne'r reioyc'd at any Mans ſad fall</l>
               <l>But wiſh a <hi>Vertuous</hi> happy life to all.</l>
               <l>This then my Comfort be, my minde appeaſe,</l>
               <l>He that writes beſt, can neuer all Men pleaſe.</l>
               <l>None e're could ſhunne, the Cenſure of a Knaue,</l>
               <l>Nor enuie, of a curriſh Natur'd Slaue.</l>
               <l>*'Tis common now, without the cauſe diſcerning,</l>
               <l>*Fooles wil find fault, with that, they haue no learning.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I write not raſh with Enuie, to defame</l>
               <l>For ſome particular wronge, any man's name,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:46"/>Shall I at <hi>Fortunes Fauourite</hi> grieued be,</l>
               <l>Becauſe <hi>Ioue</hi> made me not, as great as he:</l>
               <l>O no; 'twere baſely bad, blacke is the ſoule,</l>
               <l>Clogg'd with the horror of a ſinne ſo foule.</l>
               <l>Fairely my <hi>Muſe</hi> appeares, onely to ſhew</l>
               <l>What's lewdly ill; that Noble Mindes may know</l>
               <l>The <hi>Vicious Courtier,</hi> he whoſe Muſhrome ſight</l>
               <l>Time ſtiles ignoble, a meere Carpet Knight.</l>
               <l>A Lazie Luſt-ſtung Lord, periur'd, vniuſt,</l>
               <l>Slaue to the Itching of his Miſtris Luſt.</l>
               <l>One that admires her brauery with Oathes</l>
               <l>Much wicked-wit conſumes in gawdy Cloathes:</l>
               <l>Which ſpeakes him to the World a <hi>March-paine Man</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A very mighty <hi>Muske-Cat;</hi> one that can,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:47"/>(To pleaſe <hi>State-ſtrumpets</hi>) turne Capitall Calfe,</l>
               <l>Reu'rence her ſhooe-ſhadow, in her behalfe</l>
               <l>Sweare by <hi>Olympicke Ioue,</hi> ſhe's the Faireſt</l>
               <l>That e're breath'd, moſt Excellent, the Rareſt,</l>
               <l>Spending the Time in Commendations,</l>
               <l>In Sighes, Tales obſcene, Viſitations,</l>
               <l>Set Faces, and ſet ſpeeches, pickt from Playes,</l>
               <l>Quaint apiſh Geſtures; O the many wayes</l>
               <l>(To pleaſe <hi>Madam Much-adoe</hi>) the rare <hi>Jewels,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſicke, Maſques, Baudie Banquets, Midnight-Reuels,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cocke-Sparrow Humours,</hi> abſurd <hi>Complement,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which makes the <hi>Vicious Courtier</hi> confident,</l>
               <l>So ridiculous blinde; that his braue Trull,</l>
               <l>(Times prurient <hi>Puppet</hi>) can perſwade the Gull,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:47"/>After her Fonne to paint, powder the haire</l>
               <l>Which <hi>(catching Councell)</hi> ſeeming paſſing rare,</l>
               <l>Duely the <hi>Aſſe</hi> obſerues, curiouſly Nice,</l>
               <l>Beſt pleas'd to immitate his <hi>Cockatrice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſmell all <hi>Amber,</hi> chiefely to preuent</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lues Veneria,</hi> that infectious ſent,</l>
               <l>Bred in his rotten Entrals, through th'Exceſſe</l>
               <l>Of ſtirring Meates, inſatiate wantonneſſe,</l>
               <l>That too too common Delectation,</l>
               <l>Poyſon of wholeſome Recreation,</l>
               <l>(Sinnes ſlauiſh ſeruitude, Exceſſiue ill,)</l>
               <l>And Bane of Vertue; is much made of ſtill,</l>
               <l>By ſuch; who (rather then the Enterprize</l>
               <l>Of Noble true <hi>Knights</hi> louely exerciſe,)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:48"/>Delight in painted out-ſide, Coſtly fare,</l>
               <l>To ſtudie the faſhion, looke bigge and ſtare,</l>
               <l>Aduance the head like a <hi>Malt-Horſe,</hi> be proud</l>
               <l>And ſpeake no matter what, ſo it be loud.</l>
               <l>Bountifull to <hi>Bawdes,</hi> Mis'erable to th' poore,</l>
               <l>Sell all, whole Lordſhips to maintaine a Whore;</l>
               <l>To ſtirre vp th' intellectuals of looſe Ladies,</l>
               <l>To melt their Chaſtitie, get Baſtard Babies,</l>
               <l>Times were not ſo, when <hi>Worthies</hi> ſhin'd in Armes,</l>
               <l>Reioyc'd in <hi>Vertue,</hi> not in the wanton <hi>Charmes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Of braue <hi>Madam Vanitie</hi> the Puppet)</l>
               <l>Looſe Embrace of a conſuming Strumpet,</l>
               <l>But brauely fought for Virgins in diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Relieu'd poore Widdowes, and the Fatherleſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:48"/>Striuing with faire, renowned, valiant Acts</l>
               <l>To chaſe <hi>Jniustice,</hi> puniſh euill Facts.</l>
               <l>O bleſt performance Noble race of men,</l>
               <l>Worthy the praiſe of an <hi>Immortall Pen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your Famous <hi>Deeds,</hi> paſt ſtarres, recorded ſtand,</l>
               <l>For euer and euer, written by the hand</l>
               <l>Of ſacred <hi>Truth,</hi> to the Eternall ſhame</l>
               <l>Of the ſinne-branded <hi>Vicious Courtiers Name,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let him that notice takes, take this of me,</l>
               <l>Of Man of <hi>Money,</hi> or of low degree,</l>
               <l>Let not the hope of gaine bring that to paſſe,</l>
               <l>Which makes a <hi>Dunce,</hi> obſerue a golden <hi>Aſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor let thy Minde, at any time accord,</l>
               <l>To be the Slaue to an infamous <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:49"/>His <hi>Loue</hi> to <hi>Vice,</hi> all <hi>vertuous Acts</hi> repell</l>
               <l>As if no <hi>Plagues</hi> remain'd in ſpacious <hi>Hell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Engag'd to miſchiefe, and to villanie,</l>
               <l>To pleaſure <hi>Vice,</hi> embrace iniquitie,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Honour</hi> due for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue;</hi> that Reward</l>
               <l>Is naught (but baſe contempt) meere ſleight Regard</l>
               <l>He that will get by ſuch, muſt well diſſemble</l>
               <l>And tell the <hi>Fooles,</hi> they God's on Earth reſemble</l>
               <l>Obſequiouſly the Paraſite muſt play</l>
               <l>And hazard blacke Damnation eu'ry Day.</l>
               <l>Inſinuate, and ſo waxe knauiſh wiſe,</l>
               <l>Be a ſtampt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illen,</hi> learne to temporize,</l>
               <l>Sweare, and forſweare, depraue, informe, and lie,</l>
               <l>Change each houre <hi>Religion,</hi> periur'd die.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:49"/>Plot, plot, and ſet friends hourly at debate,</l>
               <l>Cling to the ſurer ſide, the weaker hate,</l>
               <l>Turne <hi>Baud</hi> at midnight, (<hi>Pander</hi> to the Itch</l>
               <l>Of an <hi>Adulterate Cloth</hi> of ſiluer Witch.)</l>
               <l>Practiſe to know to mixe with perilous <hi>Art</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The deadly <hi>Poyſon</hi> with the amorous Dart,</l>
               <l>Neatly obtaining, by times cunning skill,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Stibium,</hi> and <hi>Cantharides</hi> to kill.</l>
               <l>Such ſudden Fellowes, nimble in Damnation,</l>
               <l>Are <hi>Vicious Courtiers</hi> greateſt Eſtimation:</l>
               <l>When diſreſpected Honeſt men forlorne</l>
               <l>Liue miſerably wretched, <hi>Ragg'd and torne.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As for the true bred villaine, he ſhall lacke</l>
               <l>Nor Gold, nor Cloth of Gold dawb'd on his backe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:50"/>Yet when the <hi>Slaues</hi> too many ſecrets know,</l>
               <l>Oft with a <hi>Spaniſh Figge,</hi> they headlong goe</l>
               <l>Hurrid to <hi>Hell,</hi> the damned ſoules to tell</l>
               <l>What glorious <hi>villaines,</hi> here on Earth doe dwell.</l>
               <l>*That with a Politicque ſtraine, can make all ſure</l>
               <l>*Murder, with murder; murder, to ſecure.</l>
               <l>*Drunke with <hi>Conceit,</hi> that greatneſſe beares the ſway</l>
               <l>*Safely to <hi>Act,</hi> what <hi>Villany</hi> it may.</l>
               <l>*There is a <hi>Tricke,</hi> ſuch neuer faile to vſe</l>
               <l>*In which their deareſt <hi>Friends,</hi> they'l moſt abuſe</l>
               <l>*With faire pretext of Honorable <hi>Loue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>*In ſecure cunning, onely to remoue</l>
               <l>*And ſhift him forth into another <hi>Ayre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>*To purge, and leſſen, leaſt his <hi>Vertues</hi> rare</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:50"/>*<hi>Should merit Kingly Fauour,</hi> make him hie,</l>
               <l>*Aduanc'd in ſtate to greateſt Dignitie.</l>
               <l>*The Iealious thought whereof, to miſchiefe bent,</l>
               <l>*Doth ſund'ry ſecret practizes inuent</l>
               <l>*How to decline that growth, if none take roote</l>
               <l>*Swift <hi>Mercurie,</hi> a ſuddaine dramme muſt doo't.</l>
               <l>*Others there are, that ſmiling Flatter all,</l>
               <l>Proue for to each, but Friend to none at all</l>
               <l>And ſuch (beleeu't) make vſe of Time, and Place,</l>
               <l>By ſeruile ſlauery, moſt creeping baſe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Kiſſing the Clawe)</hi> appeares with Coxcombe bare,</l>
               <l>Praiſing the <hi>Vitious Gloworme</hi> paſt compare,</l>
               <l>With O-Right vertuous Lord; ſuch ſleeke Regard,</l>
               <l>Repleniſh Flat'ries Cups, with full reward.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:51"/>Like <hi>Spiders,</hi> webs of Flattery they weaue,</l>
               <l>The pleaſing Eares <hi>of Great-Ones to deceiue:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which once Entangl'd by ſome Quainte Deuiſe</l>
               <l>Chops off their <hi>heads,</hi> 'tis practiz'd in a trice.</l>
               <l>They'l giue occaſion that may moue diſcourſe</l>
               <l>And by a Tricke, <hi>ſome dang'rous Theame enforce,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To draw a doubtfull queſtion to the worſt</l>
               <l>They'l make men guilty, then betray e'm firſt,</l>
               <l>Theſe are the onely ſpies, that gape for prey,</l>
               <l>Cut-throates in ſilence, ſmile, and then betray.</l>
               <l>Intrap th' vnskilfull, beg <hi>their forfeit Liues</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To graſpe their States; thus the vile Villen thriues</l>
               <l>Whoſe whiſp'ring poyſons, ſpeakes him ſins ſupporter</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Machiuillian Darkneſſe,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icious Courtier..</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:51"/>Him, the true Noble Minde muſt euer ſhunne,</l>
               <l>Or liue (in hazard ſtill to be vndone,)</l>
               <l>Slaue to the <hi>Vanitie</hi> of <hi>Pompe,</hi> high Place,</l>
               <l>Ambitious thoughts, Sinne, and a double Face;</l>
               <l>Cringes, and Creepings, all the baſe deſires</l>
               <l>Of ſinfull Life, plagu'd with infernall fires.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What e're thou arr that careleſſe ſhalt reſort</l>
               <l>To th' <hi>Court of Vice,</hi> onely to ſee the Court;</l>
               <l>Take heed, beware of that <hi>Enchanted Glaſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where <hi>Pride in Mortals,</hi> Fiends in Hell ſurpaſſe.</l>
               <l>There ſhalt thou Maſques, ſuch midnight Reuel finde</l>
               <l>Such Muſicke, Banquets, to alure thy minde,</l>
               <l>As will affright the blood of <hi>Chaſtitie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Turne <hi>Virgin Loue,</hi> to hot Luſt's Pluriſie.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:52"/>There ſhalt thou thoſe, of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> Traine behold,</l>
               <l>Burning <hi>Temptation</hi> flame in glit'ring Gold</l>
               <l>And though adorn'd with <hi>Pearle,</hi> the Richeſt ſtuffe</l>
               <l>Their inflate <hi>Pride,</hi> ne'r thinke them braue enough.</l>
               <l>Were Gownes Emboſt with Golden, Starres ſo fine,</l>
               <l>That in each Starre, a <hi>Diamond</hi> ſhould ſhine,</l>
               <l>Still, their high Towring lofty daring Pride</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Like Luſt restrain'd)</hi> Liues neuer ſatisfide.</l>
               <l>If checkt for it; ſtraight ſwifteſt <hi>Mercury</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Strikes dead th' opgoſing Foe to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enerie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like (ſometimes) that ſad moſt Lamented Knight</l>
               <l>Who di'd by a Tricke; in ſuch a wofull plight</l>
               <l>(By Sugar Candid Poyſons) workt in Paſte</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(From Sinne and Murder ſent,)</hi> whoſe delicate Taſte,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:52"/>Vnder the fein'd pretence, of ſeeming good,</l>
               <l>Conſum'd and burnt, his vitall Crimſon blood,</l>
               <l>Such is the <hi>Mighty-Madams-Murdring ſpight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>*Court <hi>Concubines</hi> ne'r kill, but with delight.</l>
               <l>Curb'd for their Pride, like God's ill Angels ſwell,</l>
               <l>As if Earth's Diuells, and the World their Hell.</l>
               <l>*Pride is their Zeale, their <hi>Prayers</hi> forgetfulneſſe,</l>
               <l>*<hi>Charity, Contempt,</hi> their <hi>Vertue</hi> wantonneſſe</l>
               <l>*Plumpe, high-fed pamper'd <hi>fleſh,</hi> on whom muſt wait</l>
               <l>*<hi>Page, Pander, Paraſite, preparation State,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>*Gold: Gliſtring Glory, <hi>Coſt, Curious dyet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>*Inſatiate <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> and luxurious Riot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And why all this high feeding, Rich Attire,</l>
               <l>But like bright <hi>Beacons,</hi> flaming all on fire,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:53"/>Threat <hi>Ruine, Death,</hi> and <hi>Hell;</hi> which wiſe men ſee,</l>
               <l>And know what fooles they make, know them to be</l>
               <l>Soule-flaming fire-brands, Expert in Euill</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Witches, Hell-Cats, Factors</hi> for the <hi>Deuill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sucke-blouds, Hyena, Syrens Crocodiles,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis,</hi> whoſe proud ſmiles,</l>
               <l>Take pleaſure to entice, make Men deface</l>
               <l>Their Soules faire Temple, for a poore Embrace,</l>
               <l>A luſhious Pleaſure, lewd laſciuious greeting,</l>
               <l>A pleaſing ſweete, but a moſt bitter ſweeting.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Neuer was any great Arch-miſchiefe done,</l>
               <l>But by a Whore, or a Prieſt, firſt begun,</l>
               <l>A Cloth of ſiluer <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Times Tiſſue <hi>Trull,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can with cloſe <hi>Cleopatra's</hi> Kiſſes <hi>Gull.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:53"/>The greateſt <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Dukes,</hi> loue for an houre,</l>
               <l>Nor is it them ſhee loues, but their high powre.</l>
               <l>Groomes, of the meaneſt qualitie in Court,</l>
               <l>Can make her fleſhly fulneſſe, ſweeter ſport,</l>
               <l>A glorious ſhee <hi>Smocke-statiſt</hi> can amaze,</l>
               <l>Fire famous Troy, and ſet the world at gaze.</l>
               <l>A <hi>Drab</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> is a conſuming Flame,</l>
               <l>Oft, fiers the Hearts of Princes, paſt reclaime.</l>
               <l>Turnes Ioy; to deepe and Melancholy ſadneſſe,</l>
               <l>Poyſons the bloud, and fils the braine with madneſſe,</l>
               <l>*Why ſhould ſhe elſe, with painting ſeeme more faire?</l>
               <l>*Suffer her naked <hi>Breaſts</hi> lie open bare?</l>
               <l>*Why vſe falſe coulour'd haire, Emboſt with <hi>Gold?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>*Pownc'd with Perfumes, Lockes curled to behold?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:54"/>*Why Oyles? Waters for Teeth? Why void of Grace?</l>
               <l>*With ſpots (like <hi>Rats-Dung</hi>) to blacke patch the face?</l>
               <l>*Or why (in <hi>Baths</hi> of <hi>Milke</hi>) waſh her proud skin?</l>
               <l>*Why wrong Heau'ns work-manſhip, with ſuch hie ſin?</l>
               <l>*If not like CIRCE, by enchantment ſtrange,</l>
               <l>*Men into Beaſts and Beaſt-like natures change.</l>
               <l>*Confounding ſenſe, all reaſon ſits a ſide,</l>
               <l>*Such is the force of her affected Pride.</l>
               <l>*A painted Face ſleekt o're by cunning Art,</l>
               <l>*Is but the Pride of a luxurious Heart.</l>
               <l>*A diſcontentment of God's worke vpon her,</l>
               <l>*To wooe mens Eyes to Luſt, and her diſhonor.</l>
               <l>*Painting's the Nurſe of black thoghts, damn'd deuiſes,</l>
               <l>*It makes the ſoule imitate greateſt vices.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:54"/>What is it elſe? but daring Impudence,</l>
               <l>Gainſt the bright Glory of Omnipotence,</l>
               <l>Luſts Looking-Glaſſe, Torch of Iniquitie,</l>
               <l>Th'imperious Miſtris of all Witcherie,</l>
               <l>A ſlimie ſinne, dawb'd o're the painted wall</l>
               <l>Of fouleſt Folly, to catch fooles with all,</l>
               <l>A painted Face, harbours a Heart of Flint,</l>
               <l>There is no relliſh of Deuotion in't.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lust, Pride,</hi> and <hi>Enuie,</hi> all the ſinnes that are,</l>
               <l>Waites on the painted Beautie falſely faire.</l>
               <l>Still buſie in her Eare, her Minde, her Eye,</l>
               <l>To whore away Man's ſoule with foolerie,</l>
               <l>The painted outſide of a tempting Face,</l>
               <l>Spotted with Hell, ſtands ſequeſtred from Grace.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:55"/>*Such Prodigall ſinfull ſweetes, Men ought not haue,</l>
               <l>*Nor ſee th' aluring Face, vnfit to craue.</l>
               <l>*Soules that will mount, high Heau'ns, Celeſtiall ſtate,</l>
               <l>*Climbes Vertues Ladder; vicious Actions hate.</l>
               <l>*Man, that will ne'r be tempted, paſt his might,</l>
               <l>*Runnes from the Glit'ring Strumpet, flies her ſight.</l>
               <l>*O happy is the man, bleſſed for euer,</l>
               <l>*Whoſe Life, in flying Sinne, Ioyes to perſeuer.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ita nihil peius iniqua.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:55"/>
            <head>THE IESVITE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NOt like y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Maſſe-Prieſt, he whoſe mouth is cram'd</l>
               <l>With words y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpeak all Proteſtants are damn'd.</l>
               <l>Him nor his Flocke, I dare not cenſure ſo,</l>
               <l>Nor meane to write more then I iuſtly know</l>
               <l>To be moſt true; In which knowne Path I finde,</l>
               <l>Counterfeit Catholiques, ſo groſſely blinde,</l>
               <l>They dare outface Heau'ns <hi>Truth,</hi> forg'd lies maintaine</l>
               <l>To Cloake the cunning <hi>Ieſuites</hi> ſubtile Braine,</l>
               <l>He that do's Theefe-like waite for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues</hi> fall,</l>
               <l>Liues in perpetuall watch, to blow vp all.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:56"/>The Preſident, recorded ſtands for euer.</l>
               <l>In this Realmes ſafety; which hel's Plot can neuer</l>
               <l>Wipe from Rememb'rance; neuer ſhall the Euill</l>
               <l>Of that cloſe <hi>Secretary,</hi> to the <hi>Deuill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>Jeſuite</hi> GARNET, liue forgot while I,</l>
               <l>Haue <hi>Pen,</hi> or <hi>Hand,</hi> to write his Tragedy,</l>
               <l>(That <hi>Myne of Murther,</hi> Miſchiefes Maſter-vice,</l>
               <l>Lodg'd in the Politicque skull of Auarice)</l>
               <l>His deſp'rate Soule was ſuch, hee durſt to ſwimme,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice,</hi> be rackt in eu'ry Limme.</l>
               <l>All Tortures ſuffer, rather then Reueale</l>
               <l>The Treaſon, his Religion bids conceale.</l>
               <l>Witneſſe thou <hi>Ghoſt</hi> of <hi>Garnet,</hi> this is true.</l>
               <l>He that han'gd, drawne, and quarter'd, had his due.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:56"/>To him was knowne, the powder pitchie Treaſon,</l>
               <l>Neuer to be forgot, he knew the ſeaſon</l>
               <l>When, where, and how, that ſuddaine bloudie blow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Blacke, Hell-bred, Thunder, flaming, ouerthrow,)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should haue bin giuen; knew the Times ſhort ſpace,</l>
               <l>When no ſoule ſhould haue time to pray for Grace,</l>
               <l>Or cry, God helpe; The Treaſon was ſo foule,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Traitors</hi> would haue damn'd both body and Soule</l>
               <l>If in their power; and eu'ry ſoule i'th Ayre</l>
               <l>Toſt vp, ſent vnprepar'd of heau'nly prayer,</l>
               <l>With all their ſinnes; O horrid, horrid Act,</l>
               <l>All this the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> knew; conceal'd the Fact,</l>
               <l>And rather then diſcloſe, leaſt warning giue,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>King, Prince,</hi> and <hi>Nobles,</hi> not a ſoule ſhould liue,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:57"/>Here was a Villaine; yet I'ue knowne in <hi>Spaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Traitors</hi> death ſo moan'd, ſuch Credit gaine,</l>
               <l>(Though here he dyde, for Treaſons iuſt Complaint,)</l>
               <l>There Monſter <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> make a Martyr'd Saint.</l>
               <l>Miſchieuous Maſſe-Prieſts to his meriting Fame,</l>
               <l>At the high Altar in a ſpatious frame,</l>
               <l>Aduance to him, as to a Saint moſt bleſt,</l>
               <l>His Body-mangled Picture, thus expreſt:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Garnets</hi> Picture.</note>Bare Head, white Beard, Lookes ſober, in his Gowne,</l>
               <l>*Him ouer head, Angels with <hi>Laurell</hi> Crowne.</l>
               <l>*About his Necke, a long large Halter tide,</l>
               <l>*Hangs, (as befitting ſuch) downe the Left ſide.</l>
               <l>*His Belly ript, bloud ſeeming open raw,</l>
               <l>*Holding in his right hand, his pictur'd ſtraw.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:57"/>*Beneath his right ſide, flames a Heart in fire,</l>
               <l>*'Boue his left ſide, Limmes quarter'd, Treaſons hire,</l>
               <l>*Preſented on a Towre; which Pictur'd ſtorie</l>
               <l>Straw-ſainted ſet vp to'th <hi>Arch-Traitors Glory.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Inuites each eye, yea all the World to ſee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jeſuites, Protectors,</hi> of all Villany.</l>
               <l>*Poyſ'ning of Princes, held as trifling things,</l>
               <l>*With them, 'tis meritorious to kill Kings.</l>
               <l>Can this Religion be, they thinke it pure,</l>
               <l>But Man ne'r knew Religion more impure,</l>
               <l>Their Church, is but their <hi>Baud,</hi> bad deedes to further,</l>
               <l>Th' onely ſanctuary for bloud and murther.</l>
               <l>Plots, Practizes, helliſh abomination,</l>
               <l>Pardons for Treaſon, holy approbation</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:58"/>Of that ill-Sainted wretch (his curſed fault)</l>
               <l>That Father to <hi>Faux,</hi> the Diuell i'th vault.</l>
               <l>Such <hi>Judas-Ieſuites</hi> euer Traitors proue</l>
               <l>To King, and Prince; diſloyall in their loue.</l>
               <l>*Yet outward fawning ſeeme on bended knee</l>
               <l>*Low as the earth; O true hypocriſie,</l>
               <l>*Vnder the milde aſpect of Reuerence,</l>
               <l>*In duty, and ſubmiſſe obedience,</l>
               <l>*With Oylie Eloquence, beſt pleaſing Phraſe,</l>
               <l>*Catching Orations, full of flat'ring praiſe,</l>
               <l>*When in the Heart, abides no ſpot of good,</l>
               <l>*All treach'rous thoughts; all thirſting after bloud,</l>
               <l>*The fall of Princes, change, alteration,</l>
               <l>*The Proteſtants Religion's deſolation,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:58"/>*Such is the Ieſuites diue'liſh diſpoſition,</l>
               <l>*The nature of the Beaſt, his true condition.</l>
               <l>*He that can temporize, by Booke maintaine</l>
               <l>*To ſerue his ends; and glut his God-leſſe gaine.</l>
               <l>*Be what he leaſt ſeemes, cold in deuotion,</l>
               <l>Enuious, at one anothers Promotion,</l>
               <l>*Not lowly minded, but proud Ambitious,</l>
               <l>*In tongue a Saint, in heart a Slaue vicious.</l>
               <l>*Preach diuine patience, when himſelfe ſhall be,</l>
               <l>*The waſpiſh Image of all Tyrannie.</l>
               <l>*Spleenatiue, choll'ricke, And who ſo offends,</l>
               <l>*Is ſo farre off from euer being friends,</l>
               <l>All-bee't he ſeeme a Calme, yet if he liue,</l>
               <l>Hee'l be reueng'd, be ſure ne'r to forgiue.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:59"/>Such is the Ieſuite, ſuch his double Face,</l>
               <l>And ſuch his charitable ſigne of Grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that dares awe his Countrey, King and State,</l>
               <l>Smile, and yet be a villaine, all men hate,</l>
               <l>Set Princes at debate, befoole the Tymes,</l>
               <l>Poyſon the world, with irreligious Crymes,</l>
               <l>Swell Battles, Murthers, make whole Kingdoms ſhake;</l>
               <l>Shed Innocent bloud, all for Religions ſake,</l>
               <l>To defend Religion, what Religion's this,</l>
               <l>To ſeeme deuoute, and doe ſo much amiſſe?</l>
               <l>*Colour Religion, with meere gullerie,</l>
               <l>*Wreſt ſacred Text, to maintaine Roguerie,</l>
               <l>(*As if Religion were a formall Law,</l>
               <l>*Religion onely to keepe fooles in awe,)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:59"/>Defend Controuerſies; woe to thoſe dayes</l>
               <l>Woe to ſuch Serpent-ſnarling Church-Mens wayes,</l>
               <l>*Sinne ne'r triumphs, ſtrikes a more Fatall ſtroake,</l>
               <l>*Then when 'tis couer'd with Religions Cloake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That Ieſuite, he, who ſpeakes diuinely faire</l>
               <l>Yet hath a wicked life; I may compare</l>
               <l>To fire, ſtand off, doe not come too neare it,</l>
               <l>You then may ſafely warme; need not feare it.</l>
               <l>But if thou vnaduiſedly preſume,</l>
               <l>Approach to nigh, thee it will burne, conſume,</l>
               <l>So the deceitfull Prieſt, come not neare him,</l>
               <l>Shun his Acquaintance, you need not feare him.</l>
               <l>Fly his diſſembling ſight, his blacke life ſpurne,</l>
               <l>If lodg'd within your boſome, he will burne</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:60"/>With ſhow of holineſſe burne and ſcortch,</l>
               <l>Waſte thee, in thy Eſtate, like a ſpent Tortch.</l>
               <l>There's not a Gentleman of meanes do's die,</l>
               <l>But with his Heire, the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> preſently</l>
               <l>Shares in his Land; with ſhew of Reuerence,</l>
               <l>(Winning of Soules) couers concupiſcence.</l>
               <l>Commits with all he likes, any Man's wife,</l>
               <l>Makes her beleeue, 'tis to preſerue his life.</l>
               <l>Perſwading Letch'rie, with their Ghoſtly Father,</l>
               <l>No Sinne, but a Deede of charitie rather.</l>
               <l>Sad-ſickeneſſe to preuent, to ſcowre the Veines,</l>
               <l>To mundifie, and for to purge the Reines,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergo plena Charitatis;</hi> An Act</l>
               <l>Of meere Commiſeration, ſuch a Fact,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:60"/>As to denie it, (were a damned ſinne)</l>
               <l>Puls curſe on curſe, which hath for euer bin</l>
               <l>Iuſtly inflicted; puniſhing all thoſe</l>
               <l>Repugnant Natures, with the worſt of woes,</l>
               <l>Deſpaire, aſſur'd confuſion, diſmall horrour,</l>
               <l>Suddaine deſtruction, Death, Infernall Terrour,</l>
               <l>Hell, and the Diuell; for that high offence</l>
               <l>Of Stubborne refuſall, diſobedience,</l>
               <l>A ſinne, impoſſible to be forgiuen,</l>
               <l>Such is the Ieſuites charge; of purpoſe giuen,</l>
               <l>To pleaſe his Luſt; makes that, a gainefull Trade,</l>
               <l>Lies with this Lady, and that Chamber-Maide.</l>
               <l>Here giues a Pardon, there denounceth Curſes,</l>
               <l>So betwixt both, ſure to picke all their Purſes.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:61"/>The Nimble Slaues Church-knauerie can ſtrip,</l>
               <l>And fetch your greateſt Lady o're the hip.</l>
               <l>With a religious ſhow, put tricks vpon her,</l>
               <l>Rob the beleeuing Foole, firſt of her honour,</l>
               <l>Then pardon Sinne; and then he may enthrall,</l>
               <l>Rob her of Coyne, Plate, Iewels, Smocke and all,</l>
               <l>Doe, and vndoe, Her Charity's ſoone drawne</l>
               <l>For baudie Ieſuites, her beſt Smocke to pawne,</l>
               <l>Their thread of Doctrine 'mong women ſpun,</l>
               <l>Is to whore all, be ſhe the chaſteſt <hi>Nun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If ſhe denie to yeeld, Murther and Rape,</l>
               <l>Shall Wolfe-like ſeize that prey, there's no eſcape,</l>
               <l>Such is the Murd'ring Minde of him we call,</l>
               <l>Natures Monſter, <hi>Priest Ieſuiticall.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:61"/>
            <head>THE DIVELL.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SEarch all the Earth, you eu'ry where ſhall ſee,</l>
               <l>Satan moſt buſie, from the Church not free,</l>
               <l>The very Pulpit haunts, and being vext,</l>
               <l>Seeks how to put the Preacher from his Text:</l>
               <l>Such as teach others, yet themſelues neglect,</l>
               <l>And with ſinnes Caſſocke hide their owne defect;</l>
               <l>From Pew to Pew, vnſeene; Hel's Feind do's creepe,</l>
               <l>To dull the Hearers Eares, loggs ſome a ſleepe,</l>
               <l>Some to vaine prattle, others ſtill to prie,</l>
               <l>With wanton lookes, for a bewitching Eye.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:62"/>Some greedily imployes, to ſpie out Faſhions,</l>
               <l>To glut the humours of proud womens paſſions.</l>
               <l>Makes muddie Mortals, at each other looke,</l>
               <l>More then on Heau'n, or Gods all bleſſed Booke.</l>
               <l>And ſuch is Satan's craft, continuall Motion,</l>
               <l>To draw mankinde from Heau'n, and all Deuotion.</l>
               <l>Tempts ſome to Hate, Ambition, ſome to ſlide</l>
               <l>The ſlip'rie ſleights of Pompe, vn-paid for Pride,</l>
               <l>Others to ſwimme the Sea, Luſt pleaſing vice,</l>
               <l>Some wet-damnation, moſt men Auarice</l>
               <l>Seruant to Satan; Satan which do's ſtriue,</l>
               <l>Man of all heau'nly ſolace to depriue.</l>
               <l>God (for our ſinnes) no ſooner Angry growes,</l>
               <l>But ſtraight the Roaring, ſuddaine Diuell throwes</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:62"/>His Pawes on vs; And like himſelfe beginnes</l>
               <l>(For Numbers numberleſſe of deſp'rate ſinnes,)</l>
               <l>To ſeize the Soule, made an Eternall prey</l>
               <l>To burne in Hell, as Heau'ns iuſt Caſt-away.</l>
               <l>Such is the Fate of Soules, enſnar'd within</l>
               <l>Satans command; beware the Twigge of ſinne,</l>
               <l>Leaſt touch will take thee Priſ'ner; Helliſh Guiles</l>
               <l>Proue like the perilous paths of <hi>Crocodiles,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who with their ſlimie Tongues (lickt o're) prepare</l>
               <l>To murther Mortals, by a ſlip'rie Snare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Man is a Tree, whoſe Roote what i'st? thoughts euill,</l>
               <l>Bad Deeds the Body, yeelding to the Deuill.</l>
               <l>The Armes, ten proud aſpiring diſcontents,</l>
               <l>Breakers of all the Ten Commandments.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:63"/>The Branches are, our proaneſſe vnto ill,</l>
               <l>The Leafes Pleaſure, the faire Fruit ſinne, which ſtill</l>
               <l>With ſweeteſt ſhow of ſweetneſſe, tempts vs on,</l>
               <l>To feede and follow our deſtruction.</l>
               <l>*There's feare aboue vs, feare beneath vs,</l>
               <l>*Feare round about, and yet no feare within vs.</l>
               <l>Satan like <hi>Dalilah,</hi> ſuffers not men,</l>
               <l>For to ſee danger; is't not fitting then,</l>
               <l>By holy violence, we ſeize the Sword</l>
               <l>Of th' <hi>Omnipotents,</hi> Omnipotent Word,</l>
               <l>To ſlaughter ſinne in vs; O ſhall not we</l>
               <l>(That profeſſe ſacred Chriſtianitie,)</l>
               <l>Conquer our Crimes; thinke on the life to come,</l>
               <l>The riſing of the Dead; that Day of Doome,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:63"/>When this vaſt Orbe of Earth ſhall blazing burne,</l>
               <l>An all the World in Funerall Flames ſhall mourne,</l>
               <l>Then Heau'n and Hellamazing ſhall appeare,</l>
               <l>In two extreames; Ioy, and exceſſiue Feare;</l>
               <l>Heau'n in bright ſhining All Eternall Light,</l>
               <l>Hell in the Horrour of perpetuall Night.</l>
               <l>Heau'n ſhall triumph, Hell tremble, Angels ſing,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gloria in Excelſis,</hi> to Heau'ns high King;</l>
               <l>The King of Heau'n; Heau'n Ioyes perfect ſolace,</l>
               <l>All-Rauiſhing, glit'ring, gliſt'ring Palace,</l>
               <l>Pleaſures Paradice, Immortall Dwelling,</l>
               <l>All pure, excellent, paſt thought excelling,</l>
               <l>Heau'ns Pauement are the ſtarres, in what exceſſe</l>
               <l>Shines Heau'n, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtar-pau'd with ſtars numberleſſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:64"/>No thought of want, which mads the thoughts of men,</l>
               <l>But plenties fulneſſe, full abound in Heau'n.</l>
               <l>There, Virgin Chaſtitie in Life oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Glitters in Saint-like Glory, liues moſt bleſt,</l>
               <l>The poore man toſt, from wrong, to iniurie,</l>
               <l>In Heau'n findes comfort, firme felicitie.</l>
               <l>The wronged widdow, iniur'd fatherleſſe,</l>
               <l>Bright Heau'n releiues, giues all their woes redreſſe.</l>
               <l>*He that for ill, do's good; Heau'n will requite,</l>
               <l>*Crowne his faire ſoule, with Comforts infinite.</l>
               <l>Is it not fit then, we our ſinnes bewaile,</l>
               <l>Thinke ſtill on Heau'n; on Heau'n that ne'r did faile</l>
               <l>The penitent heart, when (alas) diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>Naked, forlorne, when moſt of all oppreſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:64"/>Then ſends reliefe, miraculous reliefes,</l>
               <l>Such is the Loue of Heau'n, Heau'n cures all griefes,</l>
               <l>As for Times Wolfe-turn'd ill-affected great Ones,</l>
               <l>Cloſe-fiſted to the poore, deafe to their Groanes,</l>
               <l>The villaines of this Age, that make profeſſion,</l>
               <l>Of a pure Life; yet liue by baſe oppreſſion,</l>
               <l>Hell ſhall confound their ſoules; that Den of Horror,</l>
               <l>(Circl'd with blacke affright, blew-burning Terror)</l>
               <l>Shall boyle their ſoules, and bodies, toth' blacke ſweat</l>
               <l>Of an infernall poyſon; and that eate</l>
               <l>Still to renew new paines; plagues that excell</l>
               <l>Such are the neuer-dying paines of Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There, painted Pride liues crown'd in flaming fire.</l>
               <l>The Glorious Strumpet, whipt with burning wyer</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:65"/>Fed, is the Luſt-prouoking Letcher there</l>
               <l>With ſcortching Coles; ſuch as delight to ſweare,</l>
               <l>Swallow the Drunkards euer ſcalding Oyle,</l>
               <l>There, Vſurers in Pooles of Sulphure boyle,</l>
               <l>Murther, Rape, Inceſt, endleſſe torments feele,</l>
               <l>The Racke of vengeance, and the burning wheele</l>
               <l>Whirl'd round in blew flames, ſoule-amazing feare,</l>
               <l>*More Plagues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tongue can tell, the damned beare.</l>
               <l>In burning Beds of ſteele, ſoules blazing fry,</l>
               <l>Tortur'd with torments, ſuch as neuer dye,</l>
               <l>Curſing the Time of their abus'd Creation,</l>
               <l>Parents, Fate, Sinne, and their owne damnation.</l>
               <l>Better, O better neuer to be borne,</l>
               <l>Then with ſuch Terror-ſtriking Torments torne,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:65"/>Which to eſchew, weepe wonnes of earth, repent,</l>
               <l>Weepe, weepe for ſinne, ſoule-killing ſinnes preuent,</l>
               <l>*Seeke Heau'n, ſhun Hell, fly from the worlds entice,</l>
               <l>*Heau'ns the Reward of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue,</hi> Hell of <hi>Vice.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>*Perfect Repentance, makes men brauely die,</l>
               <l>*That ne'r liu'd ſo; fly then Hels Miſerie,</l>
               <l>*Deferre not thy Repentance till to Morrow,</l>
               <l>*Shed Teares for ſinne, O 'tis a ſacred Sorrow.</l>
               <l>*Repent or damne; for ſinne weepe, and weepe well,</l>
               <l>*Soules that doe floute at Teares, ſhall fry in Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God in his infinite Mercy ne'r forſakes</l>
               <l>The ſoule which fights with ſinne, and vndertakes</l>
               <l>To doe it's beſt endeauour; ſtriues t' expell</l>
               <l>The ſubtile ſnares of ſinne, and ſtriues to dwell</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:66"/>On Vertues mount (free from the tempting vice</l>
               <l>Of the World, Fleſh; and Diuell, all th'entice</l>
               <l>Of all ill Company; whoſe venome bloud</l>
               <l>Each diuine thought in Man, each deed that's good,</l>
               <l>Seekes to corrupt, to poyſon, betray ſoules,</l>
               <l>And drie their vertues, like parcht parchment ſcroles.</l>
               <l>From which dire Miſchiefe, the Religious ſtill</l>
               <l>Protected ſtand, by the Almighties will.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>As the young Bird for food do's neuer ceaſe,</l>
               <l>Op'ning the Mouth, vntill the Damme releaſe</l>
               <l>And cure the want it ſuffers; ſo ſhould we</l>
               <l>*With vnlockt lips ſtill pray, that God would free</l>
               <l>*Our ſoules from ſinne, O 'tis a bleſſed taske!</l>
               <l>*God ne'r leaues giuing, till we leaue to aske.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:66"/>What a large, Extreame folly 'tis to ſpie</l>
               <l>Man (like the Wolfe for prey) how earneſtly</l>
               <l>He hunts for meanes; as if the onely honie</l>
               <l>Of Soule, and Body, did conſiſt in monie;</l>
               <l>Meat drinke &amp; clothes; men ſicke, ſtill pray for health,</l>
               <l>Ready to be vndone, for paltry wealth,</l>
               <l>Freedome, and ſafety; And with ſhameleſſe Faces</l>
               <l>Forget to beg of God, Spirituall Graces.</l>
               <l>*Many Men pray; But he the Glory winnes,</l>
               <l>*Who prayer, to be disburthen'd from his ſinnes;</l>
               <l>And viewes the poore Mans Labour, with the Eye</l>
               <l>Of ſweete reliefe; ther's Noble Charitie:</l>
               <l>The heart of ſuch a Man, may ſometimes ſhrinke</l>
               <l>Vnder Temptations weight, but neuer ſinke:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:67"/>*God makes him here, Lord Steward of that ſtore,</l>
               <l>*He deales ſo chearefully among the poore;</l>
               <l>*Giues him the Grace to thinke, when to his ſight</l>
               <l>*A poore wretch comes, to begge of him a Mite;</l>
               <l>*He might haue beene that begger, his Eſtate</l>
               <l>*Tranſfer'd on him; and begging at his Gate,</l>
               <l>Or in the ſtreete in Raggs, oppreſt with griefe,</l>
               <l>Glad to beſeech him, for ſome poore reliefe;</l>
               <l>To ſuch faire ſoules; Iehoua in his loue,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Giues Gifts</hi> of Grace; he their defence will proue,</l>
               <l>God's promiſe is, (if feruently, we pray</l>
               <l>And vſe our beſt endeauour eu'ry day</l>
               <l>To fly from ſinne, reſoluing to betake vs</l>
               <l>To holy Meanes, he neuer will forſake vs.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:67"/>God, is ſo kinde, he cannot, will not ſee</l>
               <l>His Seruants <hi>Slaues,</hi> to damn'd impietie.</l>
               <l>Neuer did any, doe their faire endeauour</l>
               <l>To pray to him, that euer loſt their labour.</l>
               <l>Nay more; if God but ſee thy inclination</l>
               <l>To pray; He will preuent thy ſupplication,</l>
               <l>Anſwer thy full deſire e're thou canſt craue,</l>
               <l>Grant that, thy heart did neuer hope to haue.</l>
               <l>He made the <hi>Eare,</hi> to heare the happineſſe</l>
               <l>We haue from him; the <hi>Tongue</hi> ſtill to confeſſe</l>
               <l>The Glory of his Name; our <hi>Eyes</hi> to ſee</l>
               <l>The workes of his Almighty Maieſtie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hand, Heart, Knee, Foot,</hi> God the whole man did frame</l>
               <l>All to reioyce, in his <hi>All-Sacred Name.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:68"/>And dare we <hi>Duſt</hi> and <hi>Aſhes</hi> ceaſe to pray</l>
               <l>To Him? O no; Heauen grant I neuer ſtray.</l>
               <l>Ride thou my <hi>Soule</hi> vpon ſome winged Cloud</l>
               <l>To th' <hi>Heau'nly Harueſt;</hi> Fly to the ſacred Shroud</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Sempeternall Safety;</hi> Fly the ſight</l>
               <l>Of blazing <hi>Beautie,</hi> flaring <hi>Earths</hi> delight,</l>
               <l>Malicious <hi>Mindes;</hi> miſchieuous <hi>Man's</hi> inuention,</l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Lookes,</hi> falſe <hi>Hearts,</hi> ſtampt in a foule intention,</l>
               <l>Take flight my <hi>Soule,</hi> flie from the diſmall Den</l>
               <l>Of this <hi>Darke Age;</hi> the impiuouſneſſe of Men</l>
               <l>Fly from the pond'rous Plummets of blacke Vice</l>
               <l>Which puls to Hell; helpe <hi>Prince of Paradice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I faint, I die, ſinne loades my ſoule with Horror,</l>
               <l>The <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Diuell,</hi> all with Terror</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:68"/>Hangs, on my fetter'd Limmes Priſ'ner to care</l>
               <l>I liue ſteru'd, Tortur'd, Tempted to deſpaire.</l>
               <l>Heare me <hi>Eternall Eſſence,</hi> which hath made</l>
               <l>My ſoule to pray, ſend me thy ſacred aide</l>
               <l>On the bright <hi>Sunne Beames</hi> of thy ſweet Saluation,</l>
               <l>Draw <hi>(Lord)</hi> draw vp the Dew of my Deuotion.</l>
               <l>Mount Soule, vpon the wings of Charitie,</l>
               <l>Helpe <hi>Heau'n,</hi> vp <hi>Heart,</hi> Fly at Eternitie</l>
               <l>Rowz'd like a Towring <hi>Faulcon</hi> in deſpight</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Hell,</hi> and <hi>Furies,</hi> Fly to thy <hi>Makers</hi> ſight.</l>
               <l>*Happy the Man, whoſe Actions, ſtriue to ſwimme.</l>
               <l>*Through Seas of Tribulation vnto him,</l>
               <l>*The way to Heau'n, is full of Rubbs, and Thornes,</l>
               <l>*We cannot paſſe, but by the Lane of Scornes.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16405:69"/>*The Diuell ſets his Baites, in euery angle,</l>
               <l>*No Corner's free from him, ſoules to entangle</l>
               <l>Therefore, in <hi>Vertues</hi> Path, ſtriue to excell,</l>
               <l>Let feruent Faith, repulſe the Fiend of hell.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diuines</hi> may Preach elſe till their <hi>Heart ſtrings burſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Height of Sinne will Mount; liue ſtill accurſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:69"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Acroſticke Epitaphes vpon</hi> King Iames, Prince Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke, Duke of Richmond, Lord Marques Hamleton, and others.</head>
            <div type="acrostic_epitaph">
               <head>
                  <hi>KING IAMES</hi> his Epitaph.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>K inde, Excellent <hi>King,</hi> Great <hi>Brittaines Solomon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I uſt <hi>Iudge,</hi> his Sacred <hi>Maieſtie</hi> is gon,</l>
                  <l>N ow number'd mong the dead, vpon whoſe <hi>Beere</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>G riefe through the world do's ſacrifice a Teare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I nſighes, and teares, and groanes, at his depart,</l>
                  <l>A Sea of woe broake in, ſeiz'd euery heart:</l>
                  <l>M irrour of <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> vnderneath thy Hearſe,</l>
                  <l>E ach Poet, ſadly ſits, weeping in Verſe.</l>
                  <l>S earch Earth's Circumference where ſhall you finde</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>D welling in Kings, <hi>King</hi> IAMES his royall minde:</l>
                  <l>E ternitie ſo grac'd him, hee did Shine,</l>
                  <l>C rown'd from his infancy, a <hi>King Diuine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>E xc'llently Learned; Forraigne <hi>Princes</hi> know it,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>King</hi> he was, and a moſt <hi>Sacred Poet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>S o conſtant, ſuch a <hi>Peace-Maker,</hi> what Eye</l>
                  <l>E uer beheld? <hi>His Life</hi> was Vertues Story,</l>
                  <l>D epriu'd by death, <hi>for his Immortall Glory.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="acrostic_epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:70"/>
               <head>Duke Richmonds <hi>Ghoſt.</hi> To his Princely Dutches.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>L ife of that Loue, to me on Earth, moſt Deare,</l>
                  <l>O ceaſe to grieue, for me let no ſad Teare</l>
                  <l>D rop from thy Fun'rall Eyes; Death came, <hi>I went</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O 're ioyd from Earth, <hi>to Heau'ns pure Parlaiment.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>W hy then ſad ſweet, which once my heart did burne</l>
                  <l>I n true <hi>Loues Flames,</hi> why doſt thou ſit and mourne?</l>
                  <l>C leare Eyes, Looke vp, ioy in th' <hi>Allternall Trine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>K eepe teares for ſinne; ſo <hi>Turtle liue Diuine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>S aint like they liue, where <hi>Vertue,</hi> rules high blood,</l>
                  <l>T 'is moſt, moſt fearefull to be Great, not Good,</l>
                  <l>V nlocke thy treaſure then; <hi>Heau'ns ſteward be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A nd what I left vndone, doe thou for me;</l>
                  <l>R eward thy Seruants, Good Deeds lead the way</l>
                  <l>T o make vs liue beſt in the latter day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So farewell Sweet, Good God from wayes vneuen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy Ship of Life ſteere to the Land of Heauen.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:70"/>
               <head>Duke Richmonds Epitaph.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FRom fogs of vanity, thicke <hi>Cloudes of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lockt from each Soule, ſeducing vaine Entice,</l>
                  <l>Here lyes Entoomb'd a <hi>gracious Prince,</hi> whoſe Birth</l>
                  <l>Almighty <hi>God</hi> fram'd of the pureſt Earth.</l>
                  <l>Through euery Conduite of the Fleſh, high ſtraines</l>
                  <l>Of Royall blood, ranne through his <hi>Azure Veines.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Like a faire printed <hi>Godly pleaſing Booke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So did his Dead Corpes <hi>Liuing</hi> rarely looke.</l>
                  <l>His Eyes toth' compleate carriage of his Head</l>
                  <l>Were <hi>Leaues of Loue,</hi> where none that knew but Read</l>
                  <l>A Body, ſo befitting euery Limme,</l>
                  <l>Neuer was more becoming then in Him:</l>
                  <l>But now in Graue, that Forme is chang'd to Clay</l>
                  <l>Which liuing ſhin'd, like to a Sommers Day.</l>
                  <l>Gone is the ſubiect of my mournefull verſe</l>
                  <l>His Sun is ſet; turn'd to a ſable Herſe</l>
                  <l>Lodg'd in the Night, within a death bed laide</l>
                  <l>Form'd by rude hands, the <hi>Picke Axe, and the Spade,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To put the world in minde, theſe dayes of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Death ſhall deface as if they ne'r had bin:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Witneſſe the ſad rememb'rance of that day</l>
                  <l>When this dead <hi>Duke,</hi> ſo early ſnatcht away,</l>
                  <l>How ſoone that Morne, when to <hi>Attend his King</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For to enact ſome memorable thing,</l>
                  <l>Death by the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> which writ was ſent</l>
                  <l>To ſend his Soule to <hi>Heau'ns</hi> pure <hi>Parlaiment.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:71"/>
               <head>An Epitaph.</head>
               <l>Pawſe Reader, for me thinkes I ſee appeare</l>
               <l>Sorrow in thy Face; there dropt a tender teare,</l>
               <l>I'ſt euen ſo; reade on, here ſhalt thou finde,</l>
               <l>(His Heau'n on Earth) the beauty of his minde.</l>
               <l>No vaine affecting <hi>Pompe, Pride, nor Ambition</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bred in the boſome of his ſweet condition,</l>
               <l>*Deſeruing Loue, Courteous he was to all,</l>
               <l>*<hi>A Louer of Iuſtice,</hi> Foe to Sathans thrall:</l>
               <l>*True Friend to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue,</hi> Learning wholſome Lawes,</l>
               <l>*Wonderfull valiant, in a Righteous Cauſe.</l>
               <l>*Patron of <hi>Piety,</hi> Fauourer of <hi>Arts;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>*A Noble Cherriſher of all good Parts:</l>
               <l>*What flouriſhing <hi>Vertue,</hi> e're made Man bleſt</l>
               <l>*But tooke a Lodging, in <hi>Duke Richmonds</hi> breſt,</l>
               <l>Heau'n gaue him high Birth, <hi>Scotland Princely Name,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>France</hi> courtly Language, <hi>England</hi> Eternall Fame.</l>
               <l>The modeſt garbe, of graue ciuilitie,</l>
               <l>Meekneſſe with <hi>Loue,</hi> and true <hi>Humility;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vſher'd his Soule, the perfect Path to proue</l>
               <l>The Rich content, of <hi>Great Iehoua's Loue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Round Crown'd with <hi>Glory, ſempeternall Light,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Glit'ring in <hi>Heau'n</hi> bleſt in his Makers ſight</l>
               <l>He Liues; that was, not onely <hi>Great in blood</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But what is farre more Rare, <hi>a Great man Good.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="acrostic_epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:71"/>
               <head>The Lord Marqueſſe HAMLETON. His Epitaph.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I f there be ſighes, a Teare, or grieuous Groane,</l>
                  <l>A Sorrow yet, neuer to Mortall knowne,</l>
                  <l>M ake here your <hi>Rendeuoze,</hi> ſighs, teares, each moane,</l>
                  <l>E ach Eye behold, by Fatall ſtroake here lies,</l>
                  <l>S trucke into Earth; True Honou'rs Noble Prize.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>H ow e're his Body in ſad ſickeneſſe ſped,</l>
                  <l>A ngels with his faire Soule to Heau'n are fled,</l>
                  <l>M auger the poyſon'd ſhafts of death and Hell,</l>
                  <l>L ing'ring diſeaſe; Earths Witch-craft, or ſinnes ſpell,</l>
                  <l>E ternity, ſo grac'd him, Death was vext</l>
                  <l>T o ſee him liue; and therefore ſlew him next</l>
                  <l>O f all, to all our Worthyes lately ſent,</l>
                  <l>N euer to die in Heau'ns <hi>True Parlaiment.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="acrostic_epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:72"/>
               <head>Arthur, Lord Chichester, His Epitaph.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>A dmir'd, bleſt Chicheſter, Councellour at warre,</l>
                  <l>R eu'rent State worthy; Wiſedom's Earth-bred Starre,</l>
                  <l>T o the true griefe of Kingdomes he is gon</l>
                  <l>H is faire Sun-ſet, cold as the Marble ſtone.</l>
                  <l>V ictorious <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceroy;</hi> O with what a zeale,</l>
                  <l>R ul'd he <hi>Hybernias</hi> troubleſome Common-weale.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>C urb'd rough hair'd Kerne; in conqu'ring Rebels hearts</l>
                  <l>H ee was belou'd, and fear'd, for his rare parts,</l>
                  <l>I uſtice, and Mercy Vſher'd him the way,</l>
                  <l>C onſtant to Gouerne) that could beſt obay,</l>
                  <l>H onour and Vertue ſtill (in him combinde,)</l>
                  <l>E xpreſt the fulneſſe of his Noble Minde.</l>
                  <l>S ighs turn'd to Teares, ſad Teares to greiuous groanes</l>
                  <l>T hoſe ſighs &amp; Teares, to hunder'd thouſand moanes,</l>
                  <l>E xpreſt for Him, wiſe, valiant, moſt deſcreet,</l>
                  <l>R are Fruit, made ripe for Heau'n, for Earth too ſweet.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="anagram">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:72"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable Robert, <hi>Earle of Warwicke,</hi> his Anagram in Latine. <hi>ROBERTVS RICH:</hi> Anagramma <hi>CHRISTE ROBVR:</hi> Engliſhed <hi>O CHRIST, my Strength.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>Relligio, Virtus, Pietas, hoc nomine conſtat</l>
               <l>CHRISTE ROBVR, ſacrae Relligionis Apex.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How well, thy Name, and Vertue do's agree,</l>
               <l>Firme Faith is found in that, all worth in thee.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="anagram">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:73"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honourable</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Iulius Caeſar, Knight, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of the Rolls, &amp;c. <hi>His Annagram.</hi> IVLIVS, CAESAR, <hi>Annagramma</hi> IVS, AC LIS VERA, <hi>Engliſhed</hi> IVST DEALING, AND TRVE STRIFE.</head>
            <l>IN this your Honours Anagram I finde,</l>
            <l>Iuſt Dealing Arm'd, with a Religious Minde,</l>
            <l>Fixt in your Soule, Friend to deſpiſed Art,</l>
            <l>And Noble Vertue, O thrice happy Heart,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Jacobs</hi> true ſtrife with God, for glorious Fame,</l>
            <l>Shines in the Vertue of your Noble Name,</l>
            <l>By your <hi>Just Dealing, And True Strife</hi> with ſinne,</l>
            <l>You conquer Hell, a holy Battle winne.</l>
            <l>Striue on faire ſoule, thy Zeale makes Heau'n thy friend,</l>
            <l>And Heau'ns high Chanc'ry Court thy Iournies end.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:73"/>
            <head>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERSES Vpon the Principall Coate</hi> at Armes, of my Honorable Friend Sir HENRY HART, Knight of the Noble order of the <hi>Bath.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SYmbolus iſte hominem, deſignant honore Potentem</l>
               <l>Rex, Leo, (conceſſum eſt,) Ceruus, Princepſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Terrarum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Thus expreſt in Engliſh.</head>
               <l>This Noble <hi>Armes</hi> faire Honor decks, &amp; antient worth inueſts,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Lion</hi> is the <hi>King</hi> (I grant) the <hi>Hart</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> of Beaſts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Attributes</hi> belonging to the <hi>Hart.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>Ingenious, quicke, long liu'd, Chaſte, Noble, wiſe,</l>
               <l>Are attributes found proper that ariſe</l>
               <l>To this braue <hi>Creatures</hi> praiſe; more to impart</l>
               <l>SERTORIVS, lead his Army by a <hi>Hart:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ALEXANDER tooke great pride to decke,</l>
               <l>With Golden Collars the ſoft <hi>veluet Necke</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of thoſe <hi>Heroicque Rangers,</hi> that tooke breath</l>
               <l>Hunder'd yeeres after <hi>Alexanders</hi> Death:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This being iuſt, how much more ſtirres vp Art</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That Noble Name, ſet in a bounteous Hart.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:74"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Acroſticke Compoſ'd at the Marriage</hi> Of my honour'd Friend Sir <hi>Thomas Stanly,</hi> with the LADY his wife that now is.
<figure>
                  <p>Fidelitie.</p>
                  <p>Honor</p>
                  <p>Loue</p>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>M arriage, that <hi>Sacred tye,</hi> vniteing Hearts</l>
               <l>A mple in <hi>Circular Loue,</hi> which neuer Parts,</l>
               <l>R are gentle <hi>Bride,</hi> in your bleſt Heart hath plac't</l>
               <l>Y our <hi>Husbands Heart,</hi> he that ſo thinkes him grac't</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>S o farre beyond expreſſion; nothing can</l>
               <l>T ell his high <hi>Ioy,</hi> by you a <hi>Happy man;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A ngels <hi>Protect you both;</hi> May your faire worth</l>
               <l>N atur'd like that <hi>Bleſt Tree</hi> firſt brought you forth:</l>
               <l>L iue long; <hi>So loue,</hi> liue <hi>bleſt</hi> in one another</l>
               <l>Y our ſweetneſſe grant <hi>(O Heau'n)</hi> a ioyfull Mother.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:74"/>
               <head>Verſes vpon S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Thomas Stanly his Lady, her firſt beeing with Childe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>God to this world with ſafe deliu'rance bring</l>
                  <l>That little world, <hi>Prime, Noble, Pretious thing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Within your happy <hi>Wombe;</hi> Long may it liue</l>
                  <l>To liue <hi>Times</hi> faire example, truly giue</l>
                  <l>Next God, <hi>(full ioy)</hi> praiſe to that Bodies worth</l>
                  <l>Bleſt <hi>Tree of Happineſſe,</hi> firſt brought it forth;</l>
                  <l>Thats all I can wiſh, which, to your true <hi>Ioy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Through hearty <hi>Prayer</hi> I wiſh, a louely <hi>Boy.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Hope.</p>
                        <p>Faith.</p>
                        <p>Charitie.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The bleſſed Syrens of Eternitie.</l>
                  <l>Firme <hi>Faith,</hi> Sweet <hi>Hope,</hi> and Sacred <hi>Charity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For euer dwell; faire Minded <hi>Vertuous Dame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In your two Hearts; now in one Bodies Frame,</l>
                  <l>Big with Rich Natures comely, curious dreſſing,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iewell of Glory,</hi> God's Almighty Bleſſing:</l>
                  <l>O may your Pangs in <hi>Labour,</hi> proue as milde</l>
                  <l>As was the <hi>Virgin Mary;</hi> ſhe whoſe <hi>Childe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Remember in your Throwes, you then with eaſe</l>
                  <l>Shall beare a <hi>Babe,</hi> that beſt your minde ſhall pleaſe:</l>
                  <l>So happy <hi>Mother,</hi> of a happy <hi>Sonne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If <hi>Daughter</hi> happy Liue, <hi>Heauens</hi> will be done.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic_epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:75"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Memoriall vpon the</hi> Death of that True Honorable, Valiant Commander, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Francis Carew:</hi> Knight of the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſacred Inſtitution of the <hi>Bath to our Soueraigne Lord</hi> King <hi>Charles.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>F all from mine Eyes, yea Tragicke Teares of pitie,</l>
               <l>R un to my Pen, write, write Times mournefull Dittie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>A nd to this dull <hi>Age,</hi> tell in Sorrowes Tone,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N oble, Wiſe, Valiant Carew,</hi> he is gone.</l>
               <l>C onquer'd for Loue to Heau'n, King, Country, State,</l>
               <l>I n a iuſt cauſe he dy'd; O happy Fate,</l>
               <l>S oule ſuff'ring <hi>Vertue,</hi> fully fortunate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>C all'd to the ſacred Order of the Bath,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Jemme</hi> he liu'd, and dy'd a Knight of <hi>Faith,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>R eligion drew him on to <hi>Warres</hi> fierce Fight,</l>
               <l>E arth claim'd her due; <hi>Death</hi> was to him delight,</l>
               <l>W ho liu'd, and dyde, Heauens happy <hi>Fauorite.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:75"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Epitaph vpon the Right</hi> Honourable Lady, the Lady <hi>Francis,</hi> Siſter to <hi>Theophilus</hi> Earle of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> and wife to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Gorges</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <l>YEe Eyes that ioy i'th rareneſſe of that Life,</l>
            <l>Which makes Man bleſt in a true Noble wife</l>
            <l>Behold, here lies a Iemme, bereau'd of Breath</l>
            <l>That Excellent Lady, ſhe that by Death</l>
            <l>Sterne Death ſubdu'd; her life and loue did ſhine</l>
            <l>Cleare (as Heau'ns ſtar,) like a true wife diuine.</l>
            <l>She was her Sexes wonder; hate to ſinne</l>
            <l>Made her the Glory of her Noble kinne,</l>
            <l>She was (what can be ſaid) Religious, kinde,</l>
            <l>A Saint on Earth, that bore an Angels Minde.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic_epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:76"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Death of Miſtris <hi>Margaret Brograue.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>M ilde, At Rough Grim Aſſaults, Reſtleſſe Eu'n Tir'd,</l>
            <l>B eguirt with Death, mildely her ſoule aſpir'd,</l>
            <l>R ight vpward flew to that Arch-glitring Heau'n,</l>
            <l>O f, for, and from whom, ſhee at firſt was giuen.</l>
            <l>G lory of Parents, farewell, modeſt, kinde,</l>
            <l>R are earthly Forme, fram'd of a Heau'nly Minde,</l>
            <l>A ll the fond faſhions of the world's entice,</l>
            <l>V aine Woman's wiſh ſhe ſlighted; tempting vice,</l>
            <l>E uer ſhe checkt, with thoughts of Paradice.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="anagram">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:76"/>
            <head>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my worthy Friend</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. CHARLES AYTE. CHARLES AYTE: <hi>Anagram</hi> REALY CHASTE.</head>
            <l>THe true expreſſion of a gratefull Minde,</l>
            <l>(For your long ſince paſt loue to me ſo kinde,</l>
            <l>I neuer ſhall forget;) accept then this</l>
            <l>Diuine Note on your Name; Mans chiefeſt bliſſe,</l>
            <l>Courts you faire Soule to ſuch an happineſſe;</l>
            <l>Words are too weake to tell, Pen to expreſſe.</l>
            <l>While thouſands in vaine Luſt, their life time waſte,</l>
            <l>Your Anagram, is what? <hi>Realy Chaste.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="anagram">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:77"/>
            <head>MARY HEATH. Anagram <hi>HA, MY HEART:</hi> Thus exprest:</head>
            <l>NEuer had Virgin ſweeteneſſe to the view</l>
            <l>Of this vaſt World, a happier Name then you.</l>
            <l>Your Anagram is ſuch, 'tis euer vs'd,</l>
            <l>'Mongſt <hi>Turtle Louers,</hi> that ne'r loue abus'd,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues</hi> Chaſte Queene, to you doth here impart</l>
            <l>Infinite Ioy, in theſe words, <hi>Ha, My Heart.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:77"/>
            <head>TO My much reſpected true <hi>Friend, Maſter</hi> William Vtber.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>W ith holy thoughts <hi>Lord</hi> make thee to repell</l>
               <l>I nfernall ſinne; ne'r may the charmes of Hell,</l>
               <l>L aſciuious Temptings, nor the worlds delight</l>
               <l>L ocke thee from <hi>Heau'n;</hi> the <hi>Lord of Day and Night</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I nſpire thy <hi>Soule,</hi> Rauiſh thy Noble Sight</l>
               <l>A rm'd with <hi>Faith, Hope, and Sacred Charitie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>M ount (may thy <hi>Soule</hi>) Eternall Victory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>V aine <hi>World,</hi> what is it? but a <hi>Theame</hi> of ſorrow</l>
               <l>T imes ſlaue, the ſtage of <hi>death</hi> from which we borrow</l>
               <l>B rau'ry for one <hi>Day,</hi> and are dead to <hi>Morrow:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>E arth's <hi>Pompe</hi> is nothing but a poys'ning Spell,</l>
               <l>R iots vaine Glory, Painted <hi>Iezabell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:78"/>
            <head>TO His Reſpected Friend, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>VALENTINE OLDIS.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>V ertue on Earth, (firme Enemie to Vice,</l>
               <l>A ppearing Glorious, when the Worlds Intice</l>
               <l>L aies Seidge vnto the <hi>Soule;</hi> and with delight</l>
               <l>E leuates holy <hi>Spirits</hi> gainſt ſinnes <hi>Fight</hi>)</l>
               <l>N ames you the <hi>Man</hi> for Combate; points thee on</l>
               <l>T o the <hi>Celeſtiall Race;</hi> which thought vpon</l>
               <l>I nuites thy <hi>Soule</hi> to that perfection,</l>
               <l>N o Tongue can tell; not all the <hi>Words</hi> content,</l>
               <l>E quals the Minde, that's truly Penitent,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O n <hi>Gods</hi> great <hi>Mercy,</hi> euer caſt an Eye,</l>
               <l>L et, thy knowne dang'rous <hi>Trauailes</hi> neuer die.</l>
               <l>D eeds that haue paſt the Stormes, of <hi>Sea,</hi> and <hi>Land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I n thee true <hi>Triall</hi> haue, to make thee ſtand</l>
               <l>S ins <hi>Foe,</hi> Truths <hi>Champion</hi> ſtill, at <hi>Heau'ns</hi> command.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:78"/>
            <head>TO My beloued Friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>FRANCIS HVRST.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>F ly Friend from all vaine thoughts, let thy faire youth</l>
               <l>R unne <hi>Vertues Race,</hi> be ſtill in Loue with Truth.</l>
               <l>A s <hi>Sea-Men</hi> ſtriue in <hi>Neptunes</hi> Path to ſhunne</l>
               <l>N umberleſſe Dangers; ſo like <hi>Times</hi> beſt Sonne,</l>
               <l>C leare thy Soule's ſhip, from eu'ry ſtormie Spell,</l>
               <l>I n this Worlds wicked Sea; Thoſe waues of Euill,</l>
               <l>S urges of Sinne, the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Deuill.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>H ere as you reade the Follies of the Time,</l>
               <l>V ndaunted ſtruggle to ſubdue each Cryme,</l>
               <l>R owze thee from ſinne, ſtriue <hi>Vertues</hi> Top to clime,</l>
               <l>S o from the high <hi>Pyramides</hi> of Grace,</l>
               <l>T here houers o're thy head an Angels place.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:79"/>
            <head>LOVES SONNET</head>
            <l>LEt me not be with bitterneſſe deſpighted</l>
            <l>That an with you and onely you delighted;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>(Beare witneſſe Angells)</hi> what I write is true,</l>
            <l>I Loue, and loue, <hi>and loue;</hi> and none but you.</l>
            <l>Shall I then ſuffer Racke, be rackt, and torne.</l>
            <l>Shall I then ſuffer hate, and churliſh ſcorne</l>
            <l>Will you my honeſt minde ſo much miſuſe,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sweete Natures Loue,</hi> to pittie, not abuſe;</l>
            <l>O bee ſo ſweete, <hi>Liue,</hi> and liue long to cheriſh</l>
            <l>My Pen, and mee, or I for euer periſh.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:79"/>
            <head>Sorrowes Sonnet.</head>
            <l>Once, I did loue, ſo lou'd, and was belou'd</l>
            <l>As <hi>Heau'n</hi> was angry ſure, elſe we had prou'd</l>
            <l>No-Star-croſt <hi>Louers</hi> our true Loues were ſuch,</l>
            <l>(Alas) we lou'd; and lou'd and lou'd too much</l>
            <l>For ſee the lucke, my Loue kept from mine eyes</l>
            <l>By her moſt cruell Friends; for Loue ſhe dyes.</l>
            <l>Then, like a burning <hi>Beacon</hi> ſet on fire</l>
            <l>At ſight of her ſad Funerall my dere</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Kindled, burn'd, fier'd, flam'd,</hi> as twould pierce the skie,</l>
            <l>Then would I periſh faine; but Fates denie.</l>
            <l>A thouſand griefes at once, me thought did moue</l>
            <l>In my Mad braine; and then I was in Loue,</l>
            <l>Starke Mad in Loue; all ioyes bereft me,</l>
            <l>And nothing but deſpaire, Sad ſorrow left me.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:80"/>
            <head>Vpon a Glitering Smocke <hi>Gallant ſitting at a</hi> Play.</head>
            <l>YOnder ſhe ſits that flaunting Hat and Feather</l>
            <l>Swells high my blood, &amp; makes ſuch ſtormy weather</l>
            <l>In my betoſſed Braine, I am not I,</l>
            <l>I'me ſtabd toth' very Heart, with her blacke Eye.</l>
            <l>Oh did you ſee her, trip it on the ground,</l>
            <l>Her Ratling ſilkes thy ſenſes would confound</l>
            <l>That Maske of Hers, do's mad me; hides the faire</l>
            <l>Which (vnſeene) ſure would ſeeme paſt all compare.</l>
            <l>*Eyes ake no more with looking on yon Toy</l>
            <l>*Shee'l ſet thy Heart on fire like flaming Troy:</l>
            <l>*Behold her Breaſts are bare, O ſight, O ſpell,</l>
            <l>*Satan ne're ſent a ſtronger Charme from Hell:</l>
            <l>*Plumpe panting Globes of pleaſure how yea pleaſe</l>
            <l>*My erring Eyes, and yet like ſtormes in Seas</l>
            <l>Should my ſoules ſhip once touch her, 'twould be torne</l>
            <l>And make me wiſh I neuer had bin borne.</l>
            <l>Help Heau'n leaſt gazing on thoſe Naked Twinnes</l>
            <l>I do in thought commit a thouſand ſinnes:</l>
            <l>The Great Alcides fierceſt Monſters tam'd,</l>
            <l>Yet faireſt <hi>Omphales</hi> ſight, his valour ſham'd</l>
            <l>High-ſpirited <hi>Hector,</hi> to the Field was wonne</l>
            <l>For Beautious <hi>Hellen,</hi> and all Troy vndone.</l>
            <l>A hundred thouſand ſad examples ſhow</l>
            <l>The Tragedy of Man, whoſe Eyes beſtow</l>
            <l>Liking to ſuch proud Puppets as a woman,</l>
            <l>Giuen ore to damned Pride, and true to no man.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:80"/>
            <head>The difference betwixt Acquaintance and a Friend.</head>
            <l>THe diff'rence 'twixt Acquaintance and a Friend,</l>
            <l>Truth thus proclaimes, Acquaintance will prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
            <l>Many Good Morrowes, as how doe you Sir,</l>
            <l>Prattle, and Prate, and keepe a ſtincking ſtir,</l>
            <l>Of doing Good; Their tatling Tongues can baule,</l>
            <l>Talke of much Good, but doe no good at all.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:81"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the vnkindneſſe of a Friend.</head>
            <l>WItneſſe faire Truth, is not that Iudgement weake,</l>
            <l>That will not giue a true Friend leaue to ſpeake,</l>
            <l>Shall I be dumbe, when I behold my Friend,</l>
            <l>In the vaine wayes of vanity to ſpend</l>
            <l>His Coyne, and be miſſe-lead by eu'ry Scab,</l>
            <l>To drinke this drunken health, viſite that Drab,</l>
            <l>Shall I behold my Friend whoſe faire intent</l>
            <l>Inclines to good: foole it in Complement,</l>
            <l>Talke with this prating Puppy, and that Aſſe,</l>
            <l>Here giue a Congie, there preſent a Glaſſe,</l>
            <l>Bowing the Body, bending the Anticke knee,</l>
            <l>Out on ſuch <hi>Coxcombe</hi> Curioſitie,</l>
            <l>'Tis hatefull, very ſcuruie, vſe it not</l>
            <l>'Twill foole thy Fame, thy Reputation blot,</l>
            <l>Let Reaſon rule, ſcorne not a friends aduice,</l>
            <l>Take heed of <hi>Pride,</hi> 'twas kickt from Paradice.</l>
            <l>*Sinnes are ſoone knowne, Cuſtome thy ſelfe to ill,</l>
            <l>You cannot leaue wickedneſſe when you will.</l>
            <l>The Ancient Fathers firmely ſay, vnleſſe</l>
            <l>We ſinnes occaſion ſhun, we ſhall tranſgreſſe.</l>
            <l>Looke towards Heau'n then, let it not be ſaid</l>
            <l>Thou art a Whore to friendſhip, but a Maid,</l>
            <l>Reſolu'd in Virgin loue, to liue and die,</l>
            <l>A Friend vntainted in a true frinds Eye,</l>
            <l>Be ſuch a Friend, Or neuer take the name,</l>
            <l>Of Friend vpon thee, 'twill put out thy Fame,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:16405:81"/>Strumpet thy faire Repute, demolliſh quite</l>
            <l>All peace of Conſcience, dimme thy Chriſtall ſight,</l>
            <l>From Glories view, and like a Toy of State,</l>
            <l>(Powder'd all ore with Pride) abuſe thy Fate</l>
            <l>True Turtle Friends ſhould ne'r take more delight</l>
            <l>Then in th'inioying one anothers ſight.</l>
            <l>But now hee's gon? flint hearted Friend, farewell,</l>
            <l>I'le not complaine to folly; yet I'le tell</l>
            <l>Faire Truth how fouly you haue gon aſtray,</l>
            <l>And in a wanton humour throwne away,</l>
            <l>A Iewell, which thy Life Time thou in vaine</l>
            <l>May hope, but neuer finde the like againe.</l>
            <l>Wert thou ſole Monarch of the world er'e I,</l>
            <l>Would creepe for fauour to thee, I would dye,</l>
            <l>Dye all alone, by that ſame ſword, that Hand,</l>
            <l>Of mine ſo ready ſtill at thy command</l>
            <l>Wau'ring, vnkinde, forgetfull that thou art,</l>
            <l>That neuer yet didſt, finde a trech'rous heart</l>
            <l>Lodg'd in my breſt, my Head, Hand, Heart, Life, all,</l>
            <l>To doe you right, were euer at your call,</l>
            <l>And am I ſleighted now; am I like Froth,</l>
            <l>So ſoone blowne out, O heau'n wher's Faith and Troth</l>
            <l>Where liues true friendſhips manifeſtations,</l>
            <l>Of loue to me, all vowes proteſtations,</l>
            <l>If all be fled, then I will ner giue more,</l>
            <l>Truſt to a friend, then to a common Whore,</l>
            <l>Better be rackt vpon the torturing wheele,</l>
            <l>Or like <hi>Spaines Jndian</hi> Slaue, Tymes Terror feele,</l>
            <l>To very death, then Childiſhly to finde</l>
            <l>A friend vnconſtant, faithleſſe, falſe, vnkinde.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16405:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
